<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The lives of the illustrious Romans writ in Latin by Sextus Aurelius Victor ; and translated by several young gentlemen educated by Mr. Maidwell.</title>
            <title>De viris illustribus urbis Romeo. English.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1693</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 151 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 115 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A64914</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing V342</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R13291</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13317988</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13317988</idno>
            <idno type="VID">99029</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A64914)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 99029)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 441:22)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The lives of the illustrious Romans writ in Latin by Sextus Aurelius Victor ; and translated by several young gentlemen educated by Mr. Maidwell.</title>
                  <title>De viris illustribus urbis Romeo. English.</title>
                  <author>Pliny, the Younger.</author>
                  <author>Suetonius, ca. 69-ca. 122.</author>
                  <author>Nepos, Cornelius.</author>
                  <author>Victor, Sextus Aurelius.</author>
                  <author>Maidwell, Lewis, 1650-1715.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[23], 127 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for S. Smith and B. Walford ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1693.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Translation of an anonymous work, which has been ascribed successively to the younger Pliny, Suetonius, Cornelius Nepos and Sex. Aurelius Victor.</note>
                  <note>Pages 13-14, 18, 30, and 54 are tightly bound in filmed copy.  Beginning-p. 57 photographed from Bodleian Library copy and inserted at the end.</note>
                  <note>Dedication signed: L. Maidwell.</note>
                  <note>The life of Sextus Aurelius Victor: p. [18].</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
                  <note>Marginal notes.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Victor, Sextus Aurelius.</term>
               <term>Rome --  Biography.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:99029:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:99029:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE LIVES Of the Illuſtrious ROMANS: Writ in LATIN by SEXTUS AURELIUS VICTOR, And TRANSLATED By ſeveral Young Gentlemen EDUCATED by Mr. <hi>MAIDWELL.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>Fingit equum tenera decilem cervice Magiſter</l>
               <l>Ire viam, quam monſtret eques, Venaticus ex quo</l>
               <l>Tempore cervinam pellem latravit in aula,</l>
               <l>Militat in Silvis catulus: nunc adhibe puro</l>
               <l>'Pectore verba Puer, nunc te melioribus offer.</l>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Horace.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>S. Smith,</hi> and <hi>B. Walford;</hi> at the Prince's Arms in S. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-Yard, 1693.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:99029:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:99029:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Honourable, JAMES Earl of <hi>Abingdon, &amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My <hi>LORD,</hi>
               </salute>
            </opener>
            <p>SInce I have had the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of Educating Three of your Sons, I hope with no ſmall Aſſurance of your Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction, and one of them is amongſt our Tranſlators; it
<pb facs="tcp:99029:3"/>might be thought a Crime not to Dedicate our Endeavours to your Lordſhip, that others may perceive our Duty to ſo Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable a Father, and ſo No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble a Friend. I muſt ever be a Faithful Witneſs, how Zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous and Obliging you are to promote the Advantage of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducation; and that in all Points of Generous Breeding you have endeavour'd to tranſmit thoſe Ancient and Hereditary Virtues of your Illuſtrious Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily to your Poſterity. To whom then ſhould <hi>Aurelius Victor</hi> Conſecrate his Illuſtrious <hi>Romans</hi> but to your Lordſhip? In whom are united thoſe great Names of <hi>Bertu</hi> and <hi>Norris;</hi> Names ſo Glorious in our An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals,
<pb facs="tcp:99029:3"/>that the Actions of <hi>Heroes</hi> cannot be remembred without them, for they both at Home and Abroad have highly Cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brated the True Engliſh Nobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity and Virtue. 'Tis an Injury to name Particulars, where there are ſo many eminent Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters of both Sexes, who have Immortaliz'd the former, and now Adorn the preſent Age. My Lord, your moſt Conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuous Houſe is like <hi>Virgil</hi>'s Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Tree, where there never will be wanting a Golden Bough:</p>
            <q>
               <l>— Primo avulſo, non deficit alter</l>
               <l>Aureus, &amp; ſimili frondeſcit Virga Metallo.</l>
            </q>
            <pb facs="tcp:99029:4"/>
            <p>I obſerv'd much of this In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate Worth from the Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation of your Sons, who in the various Scenes of Youth ever diſcover'd <hi>ex Traduce,</hi> a ſtrong Byaſs to Sincerity and Honour. My Lord, I will ſtop my juſt <hi>Encomium,</hi> and not incur the Cenſure of a common Dedicator, though I need not fear ſuch a Criticiſm from the vaſt Merits of my Cauſe; yet give me leave in Gratitude to declare, I am in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitely oblig'd to your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip for your conſtant Encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement in my Scholaſtick Way of Life; for your Appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation of my general Method of a Learned Academy, where our Engliſh Youth might be
<pb facs="tcp:99029:4"/>inſtructed in all Exerciſes, and the ſeveral Parts of Solid Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, without the Varniſh of a Foreign Excurſion; whence much Money is exported, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Importation of any Staple Commodity: And at laſt it appears,</p>
            <q>Coelum, non animum mutant, qui trans Mare currunt.</q>
            <p>I remember your Lordſhip once diſcourſing with me, men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned your Recommendation to the Reverend Dr. <hi>Fell,</hi> that Excellent Biſhop of <hi>Oxford,</hi> how beneficial it might prove to Young Gentlemen to have an Academy erected for their Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice in that Univerſity: That
<pb facs="tcp:99029:5"/>Arts and Sciences ought to be united, and as formerly at <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens</hi> and <hi>Rome,</hi> cohabit in one place. I cannot tell what were the Objections or Impediments of ſo uſeful a Propoſition, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that Wiſe Governour thought the Deſign and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tigue too great, conſidering the Lazy Temper of our De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate Youth, or the Phan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſtick Frugality of many Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy Parents, who are more Generous to a Foppiſh Dancing-Maſter, than a Worthy Tutor, preferring the Motions of their Sons Feet, to the Idea's of his Brain; and think the Bill of an Extravagant Taylor, more ſatisfactory than the Salary of his Induſtrious Preceptor.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:99029:5"/>
            <q>
               <l>Hos inter ſumptus, ſeſtertia Quintiliano</l>
               <l>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t multum duo ſufficient, res nulla Minoris</l>
               <l>Conſtabit Patri, quam Filius.</l>
            </q>
            <p>For my part, after ſome Years ſpent for the Publick Good, I reſt with pleaſure, Conſcious to my ſelf, that I ever did my Duty, and have done conſiderable Service, as well preſent, as future to many Noble Families, that I have never been a Pedant, but made the Gentleman and Scholema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter mix together, that I have deſign'd amongſt us a <hi>Schola Illuſtris,</hi> Comprehenſive of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward and outward Accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhments,
<pb facs="tcp:99029:6"/>and that I ſhall leave a Scheme for ſome more Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Undertaker, who may de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve a publick Support, and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction, ſo much to our De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triment neglected in <hi>England,</hi> and ſo promoted in every emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent City of <hi>Europe.</hi> I confeſs the Satyriſt cries out,</p>
            <q>Declamare doces, O ferrea pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctora Vetti.</q>
            <p>The Life of a Schoolmaſter is indeed very ſollicitous, though ever judged Honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable by all Good Men, and the Cares of it intolerable, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept the happy Genius of the Maſter, with good Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, ſomewhat alleviates
<pb facs="tcp:99029:6"/>the trouble. Then ſince my Qualifications render me the more eaſie, I will change the Name, and not the Thing, and go on for ſome time in my for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Courſe and Method with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Reflection.</p>
            <p>My Lord, Give me leave to publiſh on this Occaſion, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der your Patronage, my future Determination as to my Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment: I preſume your Sentiments may agree with other Perſons of Quality, to whom I have Communicated my Thoughts, with which I have laboured long ago, who have deſired me not yet to be tired out, but to contract my Society to a leſs Number, to turn my Domeſticks into
<pb facs="tcp:99029:7"/>French, for a conſtant Obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to facilitate the Language, to chuſe my Pupils, to admit young Gentlemen to have ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle Rooms with Servants, that we may live our Collegiate Life with more Profit and Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, excluding forthwith all thoſe of a violent and ſtubborn Temper.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Dii Majorum umbris tenuem, &amp; ſine pondere terram,</l>
               <l>Spiranteſque crocos, &amp; in urna perpetuum ver,</l>
               <l>Qui Praeceptorem Sancti vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luere Parentis.</l>
               <l>Eſſe loco.—</l>
            </q>
            <p>This Reſolution is much re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpected, and in the Opinion of
<pb facs="tcp:99029:7"/>many muſt produce the happy effect of Civility and Learning. To the promotion of which I have found nothing from ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience more Charming to Youth than the Practice of Tranſlation, and Reading of Hiſtory with the aſſiſtance of Geography and Chronology, which like the three Graces ought Hand in Hand to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form their meaſures, and have always been the Rule of our Studies. <hi>Cicero</hi> ſignalized his Judgment when he ſaid, <hi>That a Man without Hiſtory is always a Child,</hi> and therefore for its value it is ſtil'd by him as <hi>Teſtis Temporum, Lux Veritatis, Vita Memoriae, Magiſtra Vitae;</hi> from hence with <hi>Livy</hi> we are by for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer
<pb facs="tcp:99029:8"/>Examples encouraged to Virtue, and deterr'd from Vice. Thus the great <hi>Polybius</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounces it, —</p>
            <q>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</q>
            <p>But Hiſtory is lovely to eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Eye from its Natural Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and wants not to be dreſs'd with theſe ends of Gold and Silver: 'Tis no leſs evident that Tranſlation fixes it, and em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proves at once two Languages. I haſten to beg Your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip's Pardon for this Familiar Epiſtle, asking leave to intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce theſe Young Tranſlators who without any trick appear
<pb facs="tcp:99029:8"/>in their Primitive Simplicity before you.</p>
            <p>My Lord, I conclude with my moſt profound Reſpects, and moſt humble Thanks for all Your Favours, for the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs and eaſe of Your Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation, for Your Kind Wiſhes, which Great and Good Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities none Expreſſes and Extends more than Your Lordſhip; who, beſides Your many Virtues, which in Reverence I ſhall not now mention being ſo well known, are by Your Conde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcention, ſo truly great and Noble. I heartily pray that all things may fortunately ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed according to Your deſires
<pb facs="tcp:99029:9"/>to Your Self and Your Noble Relations, and that You would believe me to be,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>MY LORD,</salute> 
               <signed>Your Lordſhips moſt Obedient, and moſt Humble Servant, <hi>L. MAIDWELL.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="biography">
            <pb facs="tcp:99029:9"/>
            <head>THE LIFE OF Sextus Aurelius Victor.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>SExtus Aurelius Victor</hi> was firſt publiſhed by the Learned <hi>Andreas Schottus,</hi> and flouriſhed under the Emperors <hi>Conſtantius</hi> and <hi>Julian;</hi> for in the Life of <hi>Marcus Antonius</hi> the Philoſopher, He ſays, That <hi>Nicomedia</hi> in <hi>Bithynia</hi> was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy'd by an Earthquake in
<pb facs="tcp:99029:10"/>his time, in the Conſulate of <hi>Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>realis,</hi> which was the next year after the Ninth Conſulſhip of <hi>Conſtantius.</hi> And that in his Reign when <hi>Flavius Philippus</hi> was Conſul, the Eleventh Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tury, contrary to Ancient Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom, was celebrated without and Solemnity. Hence with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out doubt he was the ſame <hi>Aurelius Victor,</hi> who was Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſul with <hi>Valentinian</hi> Junior, A. U.C. 1121, and certainly the ſame Perſon, whom <hi>Ammianus Marcellinus</hi> mentions in his 21 Book, to be an Hiſtorian of great Reputation of his Sobri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety, and of Conſular Dignity, whom <hi>Conſtantius</hi> made Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor of <hi>Pannonia,</hi> and afterwards honoured with a Brazen Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue,
<pb facs="tcp:99029:10"/>and the Praefecture of <hi>Rome.</hi> In the Life of <hi>Severus</hi> he owns himſelf to be the Son of a mean illiterate Country-man, and to have advanced himſelf by his Virtue and Learning. 'Tis very probable he was a Pagan in his Religion, as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny privately were in the time of <hi>Conſtantius,</hi> and openly, like good Courtiers, in the Reign of his Succeſſor <hi>Julian</hi> the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtate; this may be gathered from his approving of <hi>Adrian</hi>'s Sacrifice to his beloved <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous.</hi> with the Complement of a Pious and Devout Action. Yet after all 'tis much diſputed, whether this <hi>Victor,</hi> who writ the Lives of the <hi>Caeſars,</hi> be the Author of the Illuſtrious Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans.
<pb facs="tcp:99029:11"/>For our Book, 'though it goes under his name, is of a far different ſtile, and gives you better Latin than that of the Emperors, which is harſh and unequal, yet ſententious, and may recommend the Writers Judgment, though not his Phraſe. Therefore ſome have rather aſcribed theſe Lives to <hi>Cornelius Nepos, Pliny</hi> Junior, or <hi>Suetonius;</hi> Others will have it to be according to the Title, amongſt whom is the Learned <hi>Voſſius;</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>—<hi>Si quid noviſti rectius iſtis,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Candidus imperti, ſi non, his utere mecum.</hi>
               </l>
            </q>
            <pb facs="tcp:99029:11"/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:99029:12"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:99029:12"/>
            <head>THE LIVES Of the Illuſtrious ROMANS. Writ in Latin by <hi>SEXT<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S A<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RELI<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S VICTOR.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="Austen" type="translator">
               <head>TRANSLATED by Mr. <hi>JOHN AUSTEN,</hi> From the Building of <hi>Rome,</hi> to the Year 244.</head>
               <div type="biography">
                  <head>
                     <hi>PROCA</hi> King of the <hi>Albans.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>PROCA</hi> King of the <hi>Albans</hi> had two Sons, <hi>Amulius</hi> and <hi>Numitor,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Befo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> the Bir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> of Chriſt. <hi>810.</hi>
                     </note> to whom he left his Kingdom with the Condition of Reigning yearly
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:99029:13"/>by turns. <hi>Amulius,</hi> at the Expiration of his Term, refus'd to ſurrender the Kingdom to his Brother: and intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to deprive him of Iſſue, made <hi>Rhea Silvia</hi> his Daughter chief Prieſteſs of <hi>Veſta,</hi> that ſhe might always live a Maid. But ſhe was got with Child by <hi>Mars,</hi> and brought forth <hi>Romulus</hi> and <hi>Remus.</hi> Which ſurprize provok'd <hi>Amulius</hi> to impriſon her, and throw her Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren into the <hi>Tiber,</hi> but they being pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd by the Ebbing of the Water, and left upon the Shoar, their Cries in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vited a She-Wolf to haſten to their Relief, and give them ſuck. Some time after they were found by <hi>Fauſtulus,</hi> the King's Shepherd, and by him brought home to his Wife <hi>Acca Lauren<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tia</hi> to take care of them. Theſe young Princes, when grown up, ſlew <hi>Amulius,</hi> and reſtored their Grand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>father <hi>Numitor</hi> to his Kingdom, and then by the help of the Shepherds, who in great numbers joyn'd them, they built a City, which <hi>Romulus</hi> called <hi>Rome,</hi> he having had the better Fortune in Augury to ſee twelve Vultures, and
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:99029:13"/>his Brother but ſix. And that he might begin to ſecure his City by the Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of Laws before he built Walls for its Defence, he gave order that none ſhould preſume to go over his Rampire, which <hi>Remus</hi> leaping in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſion, is ſaid to have been killed with a Mattock by <hi>Fabius Celer</hi> the Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turion.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="biography">
                  <head>
                     <hi>ROMULUS</hi> Firſt King of the <hi>Romans.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>U. C.</hi> Or from Building of <hi>Rome,</hi> the firſt Year.</note>
                     <hi>Romulus,</hi> to increaſe his People, ſet up an <hi>Aſylum</hi> or Place of Refuge, for all Strangers, and of them compoſed a great Army. But conſidering the want of Wives, he ſent Embaſſadors to demand them of his Neighbours,<note place="margin">Before Chriſt, <hi>750.</hi>
                     </note> which being denied, he pretended, in Honour of <hi>Neptune,</hi> the Celebration of Horſe-Races, called <hi>Conſualia;</hi> and when a great Concourſe of Men and Women came to ſee thoſe Sports, he gave a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Signal to the <hi>Romans</hi> to take away the Maids by force. One of which was ſo beautiful, that ſhe mov'd the Spectators to inquire where they car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:99029:14"/>her; It was anſwer'd, to Captain <hi>Thalaſſius.</hi> Which Marriage proving ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry fortunate, it was ordain'd, they ſhould invoke the Name of <hi>Thalaſſius</hi> in all future Nuptials. The firſt who made War for this Rape were the <hi>Caeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nenſes,</hi> againſt whom <hi>Romulus</hi> marched in perſon, and overcame them, killing <hi>Acro</hi> their General, in a ſingle Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat, and conſecrating his rich Spoils to <hi>Jupiter Feretrius</hi> in the Capitol. Then the <hi>Antemnates, Cruſtumini, Fidenates, Vejentes,</hi> with the <hi>Sabines,</hi> were Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federates againſt them on the ſame Account; who approaching nigh to <hi>Rome,</hi> ſeiz'd the Virgin <hi>Tarpeja,</hi> as ſhe went to the <hi>Tiber</hi> to draw Water for the Sacrifices. King <hi>Titus Tatius</hi> prof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd her the choice of any Reward, if ſhe would let his Army into the Capi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tol; To which ſhe conſenting, demand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed all they wore on their Left Arms, meaning their Rings and Bracelets, which being promiſed with Equivoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and the Gate left open, the <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tines</hi> gain'd the Caſtle, and by <hi>Titus</hi>'s Order preſſed her to death, with the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:99029:14"/>Shields, carried alſo on their Left Arms, <hi>Romulus</hi> drew out his Forces againſt <hi>Tatius,</hi> who had poſſeſs'd himſelf of the <hi>Tarpejan</hi> Hill, and fought him in the place, now the <hi>Roman Forum</hi> where <hi>Hoſtus Hoſtilius,</hi> one of his beſt Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers fighting valiantly was ſlain. By whoſe death the <hi>Romans</hi> were diſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged, and began to give ground; yet after that Diſorder, upon <hi>Romu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus</hi>'s vowing to erect a Temple to <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piter Stator,</hi> if he would ſtop his Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my's Flight, the Soldiers made a ſtand, either by Accident, or ſome Divine Inſtinct. In this Juncture the Women came between both Armies, and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diating with their Fathers and Husbands, at laſt procured a Peace. <hi>Romulus</hi> then made a Solemn League with the <hi>Sabines,</hi> and received them into <hi>Rome,</hi> as Fellow Citizens; uniting the People by the common Title of <hi>Quiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes,</hi> from <hi>Cures,</hi> a Town of the <hi>Sabines.</hi> He eſtabliſhed an hundred Senators, who for Reverence were ſtiled Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and inſtituted three Centuries of Knights; the firſt were called <hi>Ram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nenſes,</hi>
                     <pb n="6" facs="tcp:99029:15"/>from his own Name; the ſecond, <hi>Tatienſes,</hi> from <hi>Titus Tatius;</hi> and the third, <hi>Luceres,</hi> from <hi>Lucumo.</hi> He di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided the common People into thirty Companies, and diſtinguiſted them by the Names of the principal Women; But after the Muſter of his Army at the Lake <hi>Capra,</hi> he was never ſeen more. From which Accident a Diſſention ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing between the Senators, and the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, <hi>Julius Proculus,</hi> a Nobleman, came before them, and affirmed upon Oath, that he ſaw <hi>Romulus</hi> on the Hill <hi>Quiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalis,</hi> in a more ſplendid and auguſt Form than heretofore, as a Proof of his being Deified, who commanded them to ceaſe from Seditions, and to love Virtue; Thus they ſhould become Lords of the World. The <hi>Romans</hi> believ'd him, as one of great Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority among them; therefore they built <hi>Romulus</hi> a Temple upon the Hill <hi>Quirinalis,</hi> and worſhip'd him as a God, by the Name of <hi>Quirinus.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="biography">
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:99029:15"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>NUMA POMPILIUS,</hi> Second King of the <hi>Romans.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>After the Conſecration of <hi>Romulus,</hi> the People growing mutinous from a long <hi>Interregnum,</hi> and the want of a Succeſſor, <hi>Numa Pompilius,</hi> the Son of <hi>Pompo</hi> was ſent for from <hi>Cures,</hi> a Town of the <hi>Sabines.</hi> He came to <hi>Rome</hi> with the aſſurance of good <hi>Omens:</hi> and that he might ſoften this fierce People with a Senſe of Religion, he inſtituted ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny holy Rites; built a Temple to <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſta,</hi> and appointed the Veſtal Nuns. He ordain'd the three <hi>Flamens</hi> for the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Sacrifices of <hi>Jupiter, Mars,</hi> and <hi>Romulus,</hi> and conſtituted the twelve <hi>Salii</hi> Prieſts of <hi>Mars,</hi> the chief of which was called <hi>Praeful.</hi> He created the High-Prieſt, and built a Temple for <hi>Janus,</hi> (who was repreſented with two Faces) the Gates of which were ſhut in Peace, and open in War. He divided the Year into twelve Months, by adding <hi>January</hi> and <hi>February,</hi> and made many profitable
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:99029:16"/>Laws, pretending he did all thoſe things by the Direction of his Wife the Nymph <hi>Egeria.</hi> None of his Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours made War upon him, out of the great reſpect they had of his Juſtice. He died a natural Death, and was buried in the Mount <hi>Janiculus;</hi> where many years after a certain Man, by Name, <hi>Terentius,</hi> as he was ploughing, found a Stone-Cheſt with fourteen Books in it, which containing many ſlight and frivolous Reaſons about their Religious Ceremonies, were burnt in prudence by an Order of the Senate.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="biography">
                  <head>
                     <hi>TULLUS HOSTILIUS</hi> Third King of the <hi>Romans.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Tullus Hoſtilius,</hi> for his good Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice againſt the <hi>Sabines,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">U.C. <hi>82.</hi>
                     </note> was made King.<note place="margin">Before Ch. <hi>668.</hi>
                     </note> He proclaimed War with the <hi>Albans,</hi> which was ended by a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat of three Brothers on each ſide; the <hi>Horatii</hi> on the <hi>Romans,</hi> and the <hi>Curiatii</hi> on the <hi>Albans.</hi> He demoliſhed <hi>Alba</hi> for the Treachery of <hi>Metius Fufetius,</hi>
                     <pb n="9" facs="tcp:99029:16"/>their General, and commanded the Inhabitants to remove to <hi>Rome.</hi> He built that Senate-Houſe, from him called <hi>Hoſtilia,</hi> and added the Mount <hi>Caelius</hi> to the City. At laſt, as he imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tated the Example of <hi>Numa Pompilius</hi> in his Sacrifices, he by miſtaking the Ceremonies performed to <hi>Jupiter Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cius,</hi> ſo enraged the God, that he was ſtruck dead with a Thunder-Bolt, and his Palace burnt with Lightning.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="biography">
                  <head>The <hi>HORATII</hi> and the <hi>CURIATII.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">U. C. <hi>86.</hi>
                     </note>The <hi>Romans</hi> and the <hi>Albans</hi> having for a long time carried on a War under <hi>Hoſtilius</hi> and <hi>Fufetius,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Before Ch. <hi>664.</hi>
                     </note> and finding their Forces daily to decreaſe, they reſolved to determine it with the loſs of a few. The <hi>Romans</hi> choſe out three Brothers, called <hi>Horatii;</hi> and the <hi>Albans</hi> the three <hi>Curiatii,</hi> for this Combat, in which two of the <hi>Romans</hi> were preſently ſlain, and the three <hi>Albans</hi> wounded. Now <hi>Horatius,</hi> who ſurvived, perceiving this, and judging himſelf unable, tho not wounded, to fight with three, feigned
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:99029:17"/>a Flight, and by this Stratagem kill'd them one by one, purſuing him as their Wounds would permit them. The Conqueror in his return, laden with the Spoils of his Enemies, met his Siſter, who wept when ſhe ſaw the Embroider'd Coat of her ſlain Lover, one of the <hi>Curiatii.</hi> This Indiſcretion provok'd him in his rage to kill her, for which bloody Fact he was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned by the <hi>Duumviri,</hi> two Judges appointed for that purpoſe. But ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>appealing to the People, with the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance of his Fathers Supplications and Tears, he obtain'd his Pardon, yet to expiate his Crime, he was for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to go under a Gibbet, which is to be ſeen at this day in the High-way, and called <hi>Sororium.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="biography">
                  <head>METIUS FUFETIUS.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Metius Fufetius,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">U. C. <hi>88.</hi>
                     </note> the <hi>Alban</hi> General, obſerving himſelf much hated by his Citizens for putting an end to the War by the Combat of the <hi>Horatii</hi> and the <hi>Curiatii,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Before Ch. <hi>662.</hi>
                     </note> to make amends, ſecretly
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:99029:17"/>ſtirr'd up the <hi>Vejentes</hi> and the <hi>Fidenates</hi> againſt the <hi>Romans.</hi> Now <hi>Tullus,</hi> upon account of the League between them, demanded <hi>Fufetius</hi>'s Auxiliary Forces; who before the Fight drew his Army upon a Hill, expecting the Event of the Battle, with a deſign to fall in with the Conqueror. <hi>Tullus</hi> underſtanding his Deſign; gave pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Notice that <hi>Metius</hi> was poſted there by his Order; by which Artifice the Enemies were terrified, and eaſily overcome. And when <hi>Metius</hi> came the next day to congratulate him for his Victory, he was by King <hi>Tullus</hi>'s Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand tyed to four Horſes, and for his Treachery pull'd in pieces.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="biography">
                  <head>
                     <hi>ANCUS MARCIUS</hi> Fourth King of the <hi>Romans.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Ancus Marcius,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">U.C. <hi>113.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Numa Pompilius</hi>'s Grandſon by his Daughter, was not unlike his Grandfather,<note place="margin">Before Ch. <hi>667.</hi>
                     </note> either in his Juſtice, or Piety.</p>
                  <p>He overcame the <hi>Latins;</hi> added the Hills <hi>Aventinus</hi> and <hi>Janiculus</hi> to <hi>Rome;</hi>
                     <pb n="12" facs="tcp:99029:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>new wall'd the City, and confiſcated the timber of ſome Woods for publick Ship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping. He laid a Tax on Salt-Pits; was the firſt that built a Priſon, and planted a Colony at <hi>Oſtia,</hi> ſituate at the Mouth of the <hi>Tiber,</hi> very convenient for Trade. He alſo inſtituted the Office of He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralds, to aſſiſt Embaſſadors in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding ſatisfaction: which Cuſtom was borrowed from the <hi>Aequiculi,</hi> a People of <hi>Latium,</hi> and reported to have been found out by <hi>Rheſus</hi> at the Siege of <hi>Troy.</hi> Thus having ſettled theſe things; in a very ſhort time, he was taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way by an untimely Death, and by that Misfortune could not complete the Character of ſo great a King as his Subjects expected from him.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="biography">
                  <head>LUCIUS TARQUINIUS PRISCUS <hi>Fifth King of the</hi> Romans.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Lucius Tarquinius Priſcus</hi> was Son of that <hi>Damaratus</hi> of <hi>Corinth,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">U.C. <hi>137.</hi>
                     </note> who flying from the, Tyrant <hi>Cypſelus,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Before Ch. <hi>613.</hi>
                     </note> ſettled in <hi>Etruria.</hi> He was firſt called <hi>Lucumo,</hi> and came to <hi>Rome</hi> from <hi>Tarquinii,</hi> a
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:99029:18"/>City of the <hi>Tuſci.</hi> In his Journey thither an Eagle took off his Cap, and after a high Flight replaced it on his Head; Which <hi>Tanaquil</hi> his Wife obſerving, ſhe from her great Skill in Augury, knew by that Omen, he ſhould obtain the Kingdom. <hi>Tarquinius</hi> by his Riches and Induſtry rais'd himſelf to great Honour, and became a particular Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourite to King <hi>Ancus,</hi> who dying, left him Guardian of his Children; but he governed in his own Name, and ruled with ſuch Juſtice, as if he had been lawful Succeſſor. He choſe an hundred new Senators, whom he ſtil'd the Inferior Order, and doubled the Centuries of the Knights; but durſt not alter their Names, being diſcouraged by <hi>Accius Navius</hi> the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gur, and fully convinc'd of his Art by the Experiment of the Whetſtone cut <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n two by a Razor. He overthrew the <hi>Latins;</hi> built the <hi>Circus Maximus</hi> for publick Shews, and inſtituted the great <hi>Roman</hi> Games for manly Exerciſes. He triumphed over the <hi>Sabines,</hi> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> hoſe <hi>Latins</hi> who were called <hi>Priſci.</hi>
                     <pb n="14" facs="tcp:99029:19"/>He fortified the City with a Wall of Stone, and rewarded the Valour of his Son, who at the Age of thirteen years wounded his Enemy in a Battel, giving him a Coat edg'd with Purple, and a Necklace with a Golden Boſs, which were the Ornaments of Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens Sons. At laſt he was trapan'd out of his Palace by a Plot of <hi>Ancus</hi>'s Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and murder'd by their Appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="biography">
                  <head>
                     <hi>SERVIUS TULLIUS</hi> Sixth King of the <hi>Romans.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Servius Tullius</hi> was the Son of <hi>Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius Corniculanus,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">U.C. <hi>175.</hi>
                     </note> and the Captive <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſia.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Before Ch. <hi>575</hi>
                     </note> He whilſt he was brought up in <hi>Tarquinius Priſcus</hi>'s Palace, a lambent Flame was ſeen to circle his Head. Queen <hi>Tanaquil</hi> upon her Obſervation judg'd it as a certain Prediction of his future Dignity: and thereupon per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded her Husband to breed him up as he did his own Children. When he came to Man's Eſtate, <hi>Tarquinius Priſcus</hi> made him his Son-in-Law. And
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:99029:19"/>after the King was murder'd, <hi>Tanaquil</hi> told the People from a Window, that her Husband had receiv'd a dangerous, tho not a mortal Wound, and deſired that till he was cured, they would ſubmit to <hi>Servius Tullius.</hi> Thus he got the Kingdom precariouſly, yet govern'd it with great Juſtice. He of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten conquer'd the <hi>Etruſci,</hi> and added the Hills <hi>Quirinalis, Viminalis,</hi> and <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſquilinus</hi> to <hi>Rome.</hi> He raiſed a Forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication with Trenches about the City; and divided the People into four Tribes, call'd <hi>Palatina, Eſquilina, Suburrana,</hi> and <hi>Collina,</hi> allotting the poorer ſort a proportion of Corn out of the publick Granary. He ſettled Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures and Weights, with the Diſtinction of the Citizens into Claſſes and Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreds, and was the firſt that made a Regiſter of Eſtates, till then unknown in any Country. He perſwaded the <hi>Latins</hi> to build a Temple to <hi>Diana</hi> on the Mount <hi>Aventinus,</hi> in imitation of that at <hi>Epheſus.</hi> After it was built, a certain <hi>Latin</hi> had a Cow-calf of a wonderful Bigneſs, and 'twas told him
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:99029:20"/>in a Dream, that that People ſhould be Sovereign over the reſt, whoſe Citizens ſhould ſacrifice that young Cow to <hi>Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na</hi> The <hi>Latin</hi> drove the Cow to Mount <hi>Aventine,</hi> and declar'd this Secret to a <hi>Roman</hi> Prieſt, who cunningly told him he ought firſt to purifie his Hands in a clear running Stream, and whilſt the ſimple <hi>Latin</hi> went down to the <hi>Tiber,</hi> the Prieſt ſacrificed the Cow; by this prudent Trick procuring Glory to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and Empire to his People.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="biography">
                  <head>TULLIA.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Servius Tullius</hi> had two Daughters; one of a fierce,<note place="margin">U.C. <hi>216.</hi>
                     </note> and the other of a mild Diſpoſition;<note place="margin">Before Ch. <hi>534.</hi>
                     </note> and from his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark, that <hi>Tarquinius Priſcus</hi> had two Sons of the fame Temper, he married his fierce Daughter to <hi>Tarquinius</hi>'s mild Son, and his mild Daughter to his fierce, that he might qualifie their Minds by the Difference of their Natures. It happened both the good natur'd died, either a natural Death, or elſe by Poiſon. Upon which the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:99029:20"/>ill natur'd married from, the ſimilitude of their Humors. Soon after <hi>Tarqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius Superbus,</hi> by the inſtigation of his Wife <hi>Tullia,</hi> having made a party, aſſembled the Senate, and began boldly to demand, as Lawful Heir, his Father's Kingdom. Of which when <hi>Servius</hi> was informed, he went to the Senate, where he was flung down ſlairs by <hi>Tarquinius</hi>'s Order, and ſlain as he fled to his Palace. <hi>Tullia</hi> made haſte to the <hi>Forum,</hi> and was the firſt that ſaluted her Husband King, who order'd her to retire from the Crowd. She going home beheld, without any Compaſſion, her Father's dead Body lie expos'd in the Streets, and command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed her Coach-man, abhorring the Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty, to drive over him. Whence that Street was call'd <hi>Sceleratus,</hi> or <hi>Wicked;</hi> and this bloody <hi>Tullia</hi> afterwards ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh'd with her Husband <hi>Tarquin.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="biography">
                  <head>
                     <hi>TARQUINIUS SUPERBUS</hi> Seventh King of the <hi>Romans.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">U.C. <hi>219.</hi>
                     </note>
                     <hi>Tarquinius Superbus</hi> obtain'd his Sir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>name<note place="margin">Before Ch. <hi>531.</hi>
                     </note>
                     <pb n="18" facs="tcp:99029:21"/>name from his Pride. He traiterouſly uſurp'd the Kingdom by murdering <hi>Servius Tullius:</hi> yet by his great Valour he conquered the <hi>Latins;</hi> and the <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bines;</hi> took from the <hi>Volſci</hi> their Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pital City <hi>Sueſſa Pometia,</hi> and gain'd the Town <hi>Gabii,</hi> by the Policy of his Son <hi>Sextus,</hi> who pretended to revolt from him for his Cruelty. He was the firſt that inſtituted the <hi>Latin</hi> Feaſts as publick Marts for all the Neighbour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Cities. He built Galleries for the Spectators in the <hi>Circus,</hi> and made the great Common-Shoar, which Ditches were called <hi>Quiritium,</hi> becauſe in that Work be had employed all the People<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> He in laying the Foundation of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitol, found the Head of one <hi>Tolus<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi> whence 'twas predicted, that <hi>Rome<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi> ſhould become the Head of all Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. He was baniſh'd <hi>Rome,</hi> toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with his laſcivious Son <hi>Sextus,</hi> fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the Rape he commited, during the Siege of <hi>Aradea,</hi> upon the chaſt <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretia,</hi> and fled to <hi>Porſenna,</hi> King o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Etruria,</hi> by whoſe Aſſiſtance he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured to regain his loſt King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom;
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:99029:21"/>but after ſeveral Repulfes, he retired to <hi>Cumae,</hi> a City in <hi>Campania,</hi> finiſhing there the Remainder of his Life very ignominiouſly.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="Ewer" type="translator">
               <head>Mr. <hi>HENRY EWER:</hi> From the Year 244. to 388. <hi>U. C.</hi>
               </head>
               <div type="biography">
                  <head>L. TARQUINIUS COLLATINUS <hi>and</hi> LUCRETIA <hi>his Wife.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>WHilſt <hi>Tarquinius Collatinus,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>U.C.</hi> 244.</note> who was <hi>Tarquinius Superbus</hi> his Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter's Son,<note place="margin">Before Ch. <hi>506.</hi>
                     </note> ſerved under his Uncle, with others of his Relations, at the Siege of <hi>Ardea,</hi> an accidental Diſcourſe fall<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out at a merry Entertainment be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the young Princes, concerning the Excellencies of their Wives, they agreed to make Experiment of this Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference, and all take Horſe for <hi>Rome;</hi> where the Kings Sons ſurprize
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:99029:22"/>their Careleſs Wives, diverting them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves at a luxurious Banquet. Thence they go to <hi>Collatia,</hi> where <hi>Lucretia</hi> liv'd, and find her ſpinning among her Maids, for which, in all their Opinions, ſhe was eſteem'd the moſt virtuous. But <hi>Sextus Tarquinius</hi> falling in love with her, came back that night with a deſign upon her Honour; and by the privilege of a Kinſman being kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly entertain'd at <hi>Collatins</hi> his Houſe, he brake into <hi>Lucretia</hi>'s Chamber, and ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſh'd her. She the next day ſends for her Father and Husband from the Camp, and after the Diſcovery of the Rape, ſhe ſtabs her ſelf, with a Dagger ſecretly conceal'd under her Garment. This horrid Crime engag'd them in a Conſpiracy to ruin <hi>Tarquin</hi>'s Family, and by their Baniſhment to revenge her Death.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="biography">
                  <head>LUCIUS JUNIUS BRUTUS <hi>Firſt</hi> Roman <hi>Conſul.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>L. Junius Brutus,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>U.C.</hi> 245.</note> alſo <hi>Tarquini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us Superbus</hi> his Siſters Son,<note place="margin">Before Ch. <hi>505.</hi>
                     </note> fearing
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:99029:22"/>the ſame Misfortune which his Brother had ſuffered, who for his great Riches and Wiſdom was killed by his jealous Uncle, pretended himſelf a Fool, and from thence called <hi>Brutus.</hi> He once, for ſports ſake, being admitted a Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion to the young Princes <hi>Titus</hi> and <hi>Aruns</hi> going to <hi>Delphi</hi> to conſult the Oracle, he preſented <hi>Apollo</hi> with a hollow Stick fill'd with Gold, and when 'twas anſwer'd by the Prieſteſs, that he would be moſt powerful at <hi>Rome,</hi> who ſhould firſt kiſs his Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, he immediately kiſs'd the Earth, the common Parent of all things. Afterwards, in revenge of <hi>Lucretia</hi>'s Rape, he combined with <hi>Tricipitinus,</hi> and <hi>Collatinus,</hi> to extirpate the <hi>Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quins.</hi> Upon whoſe Baniſhment he was created the firſt Conſul, and was ſo zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous for the good of the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, that he ſpar'd not his own Sons and Nephews, who were plotting with the <hi>Vitellii,</hi> and the <hi>Aquillii,</hi> to reſtore the <hi>Tarquins,</hi> but brought them into the <hi>Forum,</hi> where he caus'd them firſt to be whip'd, and then beheaded. At laſt,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:99029:23"/>in a Battel againſt them, he and <hi>Aruns</hi> the King's Son fighting together with implacable Hatred, kill'd one another. His Body was brought into the <hi>Forum,</hi> where his Colleague extoll'd him in a Funeral Oration, and the <hi>Roman</hi> Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trons mourn'd for his a whole year as the Defender of their Chaſtity.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="biography">
                  <head>HORATIUS COCLES.</head>
                  <p>When <hi>Porſenna,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>U.C.</hi> 245.</note> King of the <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſci</hi> endeavour'd to reſtore the <hi>Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quins,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Before Ch. <hi>505.</hi>
                     </note> and at his firſt Attempt had ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken the Hill <hi>Janiculus, Horatius Cocles,</hi> ſo ſirnamed from the loſs of his Eye in a former Battel, ſtood on the Wooden Bridge, and there ſingly maintain'd his Poſt againſt the Enemy, until the Bridge was broken behind him, with which he fell into the <hi>Tiber,</hi> and arm'd as he was, he ſwam ſafe to his own Party. For this Noble Action the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>publick conferr'd on him as much Land as he could plough round in one day, and his Statue was ſet up in the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:99029:23"/>place where they celebrated the Feaſts
of <hi>Vulcan.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="biography">
                  <head>MUTIUS SCAEVOLA.</head>
                  <p>Whilſt <hi>Rome</hi> was beſieg'd by King <hi>Porſenna,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">U.C. <hi>245.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Mutius Cordus,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Before Ch. <hi>505.</hi>
                     </note> a Man of true <hi>Roman</hi> Reſolution, went to the Senate, promiſing to kill the King, if they would ſuffer him to go over to the Enemy as a Deſerter. With their permiſſion he went into <hi>Porſenna</hi>'s Camp, and by Miſtake kill'd a Nobleman in a Purple Habit in the ſtead of him For which being ſeiz'd, and brought before the King, as he was ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crificing, <hi>Mutius</hi> thruſt his Right Hand into the Fire, puniſhing it on this manner for killing the wrong per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. When he was commanded to be taken from the Flames, by the Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mency of <hi>Porſenna,</hi> in return of his Kindneſs, he told him, that three hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Men, as reſolute as he, had ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lig'd themſelves by Oath to attempt the ſame thing. At which <hi>Porſenna</hi> was ſo terrified, that receiving Hoſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:99029:24"/>he put an end to the War. The Senate, as a Reward for this, gave <hi>Mutius</hi> ſome Land beyond the <hi>Tiber,</hi> from him call'd the <hi>Mutian</hi> Fields, and erected a Statue in Honour of him.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="biography">
                  <head>CLAELIA.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Porſenna</hi> receiv'd,<note place="margin">U.C. <hi>245.</hi>
                     </note> among the <hi>Roman</hi> Hoſtages,<note place="margin">Before Ch. <hi>505.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Claelia,</hi> a Virgin of a Noble Family, who by a Deceit put upon her Keeprs, eſcap'd out of his Camp by night, and ſwam the <hi>Tiber</hi> with a Horſe, which ſhe accidenlly found. But the King demanded her back by his Embaſſadors, and had her reſtor'd, yet was ſo great an Admirer of her Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, that he gave her leave to return to <hi>Rome,</hi> with any other Hoſtages ſhe ſhould deſire, ſhe choſe the young Men and Maids whom ſhe knew were moſt expos'd to the Violence of the Soldiers. For which brave Action, the <hi>Romans</hi> ſet up her Statue on Horſe-back in the <hi>Forum.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="biography">
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:99029:24"/>
                  <head>The three hundred and ſix <hi>FABII.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">U.C. <hi>274.</hi>
                     </note>In the War between the <hi>Romans</hi> and the <hi>Veientes,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Before Ch. <hi>476.</hi>
                     </note> the <hi>Fabian</hi> Family pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd to the Senate, the carrying it on by themſelves at their proper Expence. They marched out three hundred and ſix, under the Command of <hi>Fabius</hi> the Conſul, and after great Succeſs in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Skirmiſhes, encamp'd at the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver <hi>Cremera.</hi> But the <hi>Veientes</hi> who put their greateſt Confidence in Strata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gems, plac'd Cattle in Veiw on the other ſide, which the <hi>Fabii</hi> going to ſeize, fell into an Ambuſh, and were all cut off. The day therefore whereon this happened was numbered in the Calen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dar amongſt the Unfortunate, and the Gate at which they went out, call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Scelerata,</hi> or Unhappy. One only of that Family, by reaſon of his Mino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, was left at home; and from him the Name was continued to <hi>Fabius Maxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus,</hi> who by his avoiding Battel, much weakened <hi>Hannibal</hi>'s Army; for which by his Detractors he was nam'd <hi>Cuncta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     </hi> or Delayer.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="biography">
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:99029:25"/>
                  <head>PUBLIUS VALERIUS POPLICOLA.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Publius Valerius,</hi> the Son of <hi>Voluſus,</hi> triumphed three times;<note place="margin">U.C. <hi>245.</hi>
                     </note> firſt over the <hi>Veientes,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Before Ch. <hi>505.</hi>
                     </note> then over the <hi>Sabines,</hi> and laſtly over them both. But becauſe he choſe no Conſul, in place of <hi>Brutus</hi> his Colleague, and dwelt in <hi>Velia</hi> a place of great ſtrength in <hi>Rome,</hi> he was ſuſpected to have aim'd at the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment. At his knowledge hereof being much diſturbed, he complain'd to the People for entertaining ſuch ill thoughts of him, and to juſtifie himſelf, he ſent preſently to have his Houſe pull'd down. He alſo order'd the car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying of Rods without Axes in the City, and laid them down as a Mark of Reſpect before a popular Aſſembly, making a Law for appealing from the Magiſtrates to the People; for which Popularity he was called <hi>Poplicola.</hi> And after four Conſulſhips died ſo poor, that he was buried by publick Collection, and mourn'd for one year
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:99029:25"/>by the Matrons, as <hi>Brutus</hi> his Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>league had been before him.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="biography">
                  <head>AULUS POSTHUMIUS.</head>
                  <p>King <hi>Tarquin</hi> after his Baniſhment fled to <hi>Mamilius,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">U.C. <hi>257.</hi>
                     </note> Lord of <hi>Tuſculum</hi> his Son-in-Law,<note place="margin">Before Ch. <hi>493.</hi>
                     </note> who with the Aſſiſtance of the <hi>Latins,</hi> ingaged the <hi>Romans</hi> in great Difficulties. They choſe therefore <hi>Aulus Poſthumius</hi> Dictator, who fought the Enemy at the Lake <hi>Regillus,</hi> where when the Victory was doubtful, <hi>Coſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus,</hi> the General of the Horſe, uſed this Stratagem, he order'd them to unbridle their Horſes, that it might be impoſſible in their Charge to ſtop their Carrier. By which rough ſhock they routed the <hi>Latins,</hi> and took their Camp. In this Action were obſerv'd, among them two young Men very remarkable for their Valour, mounted on white Horſes, whom the Dictator, after a ſearch for, that he might reward them according to their Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, could not find, therefore ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing them to be <hi>Caſtor</hi> and <hi>Pollux,</hi> he
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:99029:26"/>conſecrated a Temple to them both.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="biography">
                  <head>L. QUINCTIUS CINCINNATUS.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">U.C. <hi>292.</hi>
                     </note>The Juſtice of <hi>Lucius Quinctius Cin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinnatus</hi> was very exemplary in diſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heriting his undutiful Son <hi>Kaeſo,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Before Ch. <hi>458.</hi>
                     </note> who to revenge that, and the Scandal laid upon him by the Cenſors, fled to the <hi>Volſci,</hi> and the <hi>Sabines,</hi> then in War with the <hi>Romans,</hi> under the Command of <hi>Claelius Gracchus,</hi> by whom <hi>Q. Minutius</hi> the Conſul, with his Army, was block'd up in Mount <hi>Algidus.</hi> But <hi>Quin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctius</hi> being made Dictator, the Meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers that carried his Commiſſion, found him ploughing without his Cloaths, beyond the <hi>Tiber,</hi> where putting on his Robe he march'd directly thither, and freed the Conſul; for which he was preſented by <hi>Minucius</hi> with a Crown call'd <hi>Obſidionalis,</hi> particular to thoſe who had valiantly rais'd a Siege. He totally routed the Enemy, took their General Priſoner, and made him walk before his Triumphal Chariot. This War was ſo ſoon ended, that he
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:99029:26"/>laid down his Dictatorſhip the ſixteenth day after he had receiv'd it, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn'd again to his Affairs in the Country. In a ſecond Dictatorſhip, twenty years after, he commanded <hi>Servilius Ahala,</hi> General of the Horſe, to execute <hi>Spurius Maelius,</hi> who ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly aim'd at the Subverſion of the Government; and pull'd down his Houſe; From whence that place was call'd <hi>Aequimolium.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="biography">
                  <head>MENENIUS AGRIPPA LANATUS.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Menenius Agrippa,</hi> ſirnamed <hi>Lanatus,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">U.C. <hi>259.</hi>
                     </note> was choſen General againſt the <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bines,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Before Ch. <hi>491.</hi>
                     </note> and triumph'd for his Victory over them. In his time the People mutined againſt the Senators, and march'd out of <hi>Rome</hi> to the Sacred Hill, not able any longer to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure the Burden of their Taxes, and the continual Services of the War, nor would be brought back to their Dwellings. <hi>Agrippa</hi> therefore told them this Fable; <hi>Once the parts of the Body ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:99029:27"/>the Belly to he idle, and uſeleſs quarrel'd, and denied it their aſſiſtance But when by this Folly they themſelves be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to grow weak, and underſtood that the Meat which the Belly receiv'd wat diſpos'd by its power through the other Members they were ſoon reconcil'd. Thus the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate and the People; as one Body, b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Diſcord are ruin'd, but by Concord flouriſh</hi> By this Moral he reduc'd the ſtubborn Multitude, and created Tribunes o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the People to defend their Liberty, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Haughtineſs of the Nobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity. This <hi>Menenius</hi> died ſo poor, that the People made a Collection for his Funeral, and the Senate ſet up a Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nument for him at the publick Charge.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="biography">
                  <head>C. MARCIUS CORIOLANUS.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Caius Marcius</hi> ſtil'd <hi>Coriolanus,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">U.C. <hi>260.</hi>
                     </note> from his taking <hi>Corioli,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Before Ch. <hi>490.</hi>
                     </note> a City of the <hi>Volſci,</hi> when his General <hi>Poſthumius</hi> offer'd him any Reward he would ask, for the brave Actions he perform'd in that War, he, an eminent Example of Valor,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:99029:27"/>and Friendſhep, only took a Horſe, and a Friend of his, who was amongſt the Captives. In his Conſulſhip, when Proviſions were ſcarce, Corn by his Order was brought out of <hi>Sicily,</hi> and ſold to the People at a dear rate; that he might conſtrain them by this Severity to mind their Husbandry, and not promote Sedition. Upon an Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſation by <hi>Decius,</hi> Tribune of the People, he was baniſh'd, and flying to the <hi>Volſci,</hi> ſided with them, under the Command of <hi>Attius Tullus,</hi> againſt the <hi>Romans,</hi> encamping within four Miles of the City: And would not be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peas'd by any Embaſſy from <hi>Rome;</hi> till at laſt, by the Interceſſion of his Mother <hi>Vetruria,</hi> and his Wife <hi>Volumnia,</hi> with a great number of Matrons in their Retinue; he put an end to the War, and was afterwards put to death as a Traitor, by the <hi>Volſci.</hi> For this there was a Temple built, <hi>Fortunae Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liebri, To Good Fortune procur'd by Women.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="biography">
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:99029:28"/>
                  <head>C. LICINIUS STOLO.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Fabius Ambuſtus</hi> had two Daughters,<note place="margin">U.C. <hi>388.</hi>
                     </note> whom he married,<note place="margin">Before Ch. <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>62.</hi>
                     </note> one to <hi>Licinius Stolo,</hi> a Plebeian, the other to <hi>Aulus Sulpitius,</hi> a Nobleman. The Wife of the Ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beian making a Viſit to her Siſter, whoſe Husband was Tribune of the Soldiers, at that time of equal Power with a Conſul, diſcover'd her ill Breed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by her Fright at the ſight of the Rods and Axes plac'd by the Lictors at the Door, for which her Siſter deriding her, ſhe complain'd of the Affront to her Husband, who by the aſſiſtance of his Father-in-law, when he was made Tribune of the People, eſtabliſh'd a Law, that one of the Conſuls ſhould always be choſen out of the Commoners. This, altho much oppos'd by <hi>Appius Claudius,</hi> took effect; and <hi>Licinius Stolo</hi> was firſt created Conſul. He alſo made another Law, that no Plebeian ſhould have above five hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Acres of Land; and yet he ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving five hundred Acres in his own
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:99029:28"/>Right, enjoy'd as much more in the Name of his Son, who was out of his Tuition, for which Violation, he was call'd to an Account; and was the firſt that ſuffer'd by his own Act.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="Temple" type="translator">
               <head>Mr. <hi>RICHARD TEMPLE.</hi> From the Year 302. to 434. <hi>U. C.</hi>
               </head>
               <div type="biography">
                  <head>LUCIUS VIRGINIUS <hi>the Centurion.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">U.C. <hi>104.</hi>
                     </note>WHen the <hi>Roman</hi> People could no longer bear the Inſolence of their Factious Tribunes,<note place="margin">Before Ch. <hi>446.</hi>
                     </note> they ſet up the <hi>Decemviri,</hi> who by their Office drew up new Laws upon twelve Tables, collected from thoſe which <hi>Solon</hi> gave the <hi>Athenians:</hi> and whilſt theſe Ten Magiſtrates were deſigning by agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to continue the Government a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt themſelves, one of them, by
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:99029:29"/>Name <hi>Appius Claudius,</hi> fell paſſionately in Love with <hi>Virginia,</hi> the beautiful Daughter of <hi>Virginius</hi> the Centurion, then in the Service of the State at <hi>Algidum.</hi> Which Maid, when he could by no means debauch, he ſuborn'd his Client <hi>Marcus Claudius</hi> to demand her for his Slave, as born in his Family, but ſtoln away by <hi>Virginius.</hi> He thought his Point not hard to gain, ſince he himſelf was to be both Judge and Party. Her Father knowing this came to <hi>Rome</hi> on the very day of her Trial, where finding his Daughter caſt, he deſired leave to take his laſt Farewel of her; ſo going aſide, as it were, for private Diſcourſe, ſtabb'd her, and throwing her Body on his Shoulders, fled to the Army; by that fad Spectacle animating the Soldiers to revenge that Crime. They firſt creating ten Military Tribunes, ſeized on Mount <hi>Aventinus,</hi> forc'd the <hi>Decem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viri</hi> to abdicate their Power, and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh'd them all either by Death or Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, only <hi>Appius Claudius</hi> was found dead in Priſon.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="biography">
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:99029:29"/>
                  <head>The Image of <hi>AESCULAPIUS</hi> brought to <hi>Rome.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">U.C. <hi>462.</hi>
                     </note>The <hi>Romans</hi> afflicted with a grievous Peſtilence,<note place="margin">Before Ch. <hi>288.</hi>
                     </note> ſent to conſult the Oracle of <hi>Apollo</hi> at <hi>Delphi,</hi> and being order'd to fetch the Image of <hi>Aeſculapius</hi> from <hi>Epidaurum</hi> a City of <hi>Epirus,</hi> they im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately diſpatch'd away ten Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadors, of whom <hi>Quintus Ogulnius</hi> was chief in the Commiſſion. As ſoon as they enter'd the Temple, and were wondring at the Largeneſs of the Statue, a Snake crept from under the Pedeſtal, which rather moved Reſpect than Fear, and gliding through the middle of the Town, to the admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of all, went into the <hi>Roman</hi> Gally, and rolled it ſelf up in <hi>Ogulnius</hi> his Cabin. They came with the God as far as <hi>Antium,</hi> a Port in <hi>Italy,</hi> where the Sea being very rough, the Snake leapt over Board, and went directly to the Neighbouring Temple of <hi>Aeſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lapius:</hi> yet after ſome few days return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the Gally, and as they row'd up
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:99029:30"/>the <hi>Tiber,</hi> it leap'd into the little Iſland, that was form'd of <hi>Tarquin</hi>'s Palace, thrown into the River, where a Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple was built to <hi>Aeſculapius,</hi> and the Plague ſuddenly ſtop'd.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="biography">
                  <head>FURIUS CAMILLUS.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">U.C. <hi>358.</hi>
                     </note>When <hi>Furius Camillus</hi> beſieged the <hi>Faliſci,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Before Ch. <hi>392.</hi>
                     </note> the Schoolmaſter of the Town, by a pretence of taking a Walk, came over to him with moſt of the chief Citizens Sons; but inſtead of being kindly received by <hi>Camillus,</hi> he was orderd for his Perfidiouſneſs to be bound and whip'd back into the Town by his Scholars: which oblig'd the <hi>Faliſci,</hi> tranſported with ſuch a remarkable Act of Juſtice, to yield up themſelves, and their Town to him. He had the Honour of a Triumph for taking the City <hi>Veii</hi> after ten years Siege, yet was accuſed for having had his Triumphal Chariot drawn with white Horſes, an Honour only lawful in the proceſſion of <hi>Jupiter,</hi> and the <hi>Sun;</hi> alſo that he had unequally
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:99029:30"/>divided the Plunder they tool at the Sacking of <hi>Veii:</hi> for which, cited to his Tryal by <hi>Apuleius</hi> the Tribune of the People, he was found guilty, and baniſh'd to <hi>Ardea.</hi> About this time the <hi>Galli Senones</hi> forſaking their own Country for its Barrenneſs, came into <hi>Italy,</hi> and beſieged <hi>Cluſium,</hi> a Town in <hi>Etruria.</hi> Three Embaſſadors were ſent from <hi>Rome</hi> to adviſe them to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt from their Enterpriſe, and one of them, by name <hi>Quintus Fabius,</hi> in a Battle, contrary to the Law of Nations, kill'd the General of the <hi>Gauls;</hi> This ſo enrag'd them, that upon denial of ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rendring the Embaſſadors, according to their Command, they march'd di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly towards <hi>Rome,</hi> and beat the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans</hi> on the ſixteenth of the Kalends of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> at the River <hi>Alia,</hi> which Day was ever after reckon'd in the Ka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lendar amongſt the <hi>Nefaſti,</hi> or Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lucky, and call'd <hi>Alienſis.</hi> The con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quering <hi>Gauls</hi> enter'd the City, and at firſt ſight of the Senators, dreſs'd in their Robes, and ſitting in their Ivory Chairs, worſhip's them as the Tutelar
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:99029:31"/>Gods of the Place; but when they found them to be Men, they kill'd them with all imaginable Contempt. The Remainder of the Youth fled with <hi>Manlius</hi> to the Capitol, and there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieg'd by the <hi>Gauls,</hi> were freed by the ſingular Valour of <hi>Camillus,</hi> who in his abſence was choſen Dictator, and having gather'd the ſcatter'd Troops of of the <hi>Roman</hi> Army, ſurprizing the <hi>Gauls</hi> by a ſudden Onſet, gain'd an ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute Victory over them: by his ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, the <hi>Romans</hi> rebuilt their burnt Houſes, and were hinder'd from ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tling themſelves at <hi>Veii.</hi> Thus he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor'd the City to her Citizens, and the Citizens to their City.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="biography">
                  <head>MARCUS MANLIUS CA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>PITOLINUS.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Manlius,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">U.C. <hi>365.</hi>
                     </note> for the Repulſe he gave the <hi>Gauls</hi> at the Capitol,<note place="margin">Before Ch. <hi>385.</hi>
                     </note> call'd <hi>Capitolinus</hi> ſerv'd ſixteen years as Voluntier in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Army, he had ſeven and thirty Mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary Rewards given him, and thre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> and thirty Honorable Scars on hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="39" facs="tcp:99029:31"/>Breaſt. It was he, when the City was taken, that advis'd the Remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the <hi>Romans</hi> to fly to the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitol, and one night allarm'd by the Gabling of a Gooſe, beat off the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, ſcaling the Hill; for which Action he was ſtil'd Patron by his Citizens, who in Gratitude brought him a Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>native of Corn out of their particular Allowance, tho they were in great want of it themſelves, and gave him a Houſe, at the publick Charge in the Capitol. Theſe Honours ſo puff'd him up, that he created himſelf many Enemies, and was accus'd by the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, for not having made a juſt Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtribution of the Plunder, he had ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken from the <hi>Gauls:</hi> alſo for paying out of his own Eſtate the Debts of thoſe, who according to Law, had been turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed over as Slaves to their Creditors: he was thrown into Priſon, upon ſuſpicion of aiming at the Crown, but ſet at Liberty by the unanimous Vote of the People: relapſing into the ſame Crime, and perſevering in it, he was found guilty: yet upon his looking
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:99029:32" rendition="simple:additions"/>towards the Capitol, and the Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of his good Service perform'd there, he was repriev'd, but then condemn'd in another place, was thrown down the <hi>Tarpejan</hi> Rock. His Houſe was demoliſh'd, his Goods confiſcated, and the <hi>Manlii</hi> ever after oblig'd to renounce the <hi>Praenomen</hi> of <hi>Marcus.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="biography">
                  <head>AULUS CORNELIUS COS<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SUS.</head>
                  <p>The <hi>Fidenates,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">U.C. <hi>318.</hi>
                     </note> ancient Enemies of the <hi>Romans,</hi> that they might fight without any hope of Pardon,<note place="margin">Before Ch. <hi>432.</hi>
                     </note> kill'd the <hi>Roman</hi> Embaſſadors that were in Treaty with them, againſt whom <hi>Quinctus Cincinnatus</hi> was ſent Dictator, with <hi>Cornelius Coſſus,</hi> General of the Horſe, who with his own hand kill'd King <hi>Lartes Tolumnius,</hi> and was the ſecond from <hi>Romulus,</hi> that conſecrated the Spoils of a ſlain General to <hi>Jupiter Feretrius.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="biography">
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:99029:32"/>
                  <head>PUBLIUS DECIUS <hi>the Father.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">U.C. <hi>417.</hi>
                     </note>
                     <hi>Publius Decius Mus</hi> was Tribune of the Soldiers in the <hi>Samnite</hi> War,<note place="margin">Before Ch. <hi>333.</hi>
                     </note> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <hi>Valerius Maximus,</hi> and <hi>Cornelius Coſſus</hi> the Conſuls. When they were block'd up by an Ambuſh of the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, in the narrow Paſs of the Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain <hi>Gaurus</hi> in <hi>Campania,</hi> he with a Detachment granted him upon his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt again'd an Hill, frighten'd the Enemy, and at Midnight eſcap'd ſafe through their ſleeping Guards. For which conſiderable Service, the Army preſented him with an Oaken Crown, called <hi>Civica,</hi> the honourable Reward of ſuch as ſav'd the Life of a Citizen in Battel, and with another nam'd <hi>Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidionalis,</hi> for raiſing the Siege. In the <hi>Latin</hi> War he and his Colleague <hi>Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius Torquatus</hi> encamp'd at the River <hi>Veſeris,</hi> where both the Conſuls dream'd, the ſame night, the Conqueſt would be theirs, whoſe General ſhould fall in the Battel, comparing their
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:99029:33"/>Dreams, they agreed, that he, whoſe Wing happened to be worſted, ſhou'd vow himſelf to the Infernal Gods, the Left Wing, which <hi>Decius</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, giving way, he with great reſolution repeating ſome Solemn Prayers after <hi>Valerius</hi> the High-Prieſt, devoted himſelf with his Enemies to the Infernal Gods, ſo ruſhing into the Battel, by his death, procured Victory to the <hi>Romans.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="biography">
                  <head>P. DECIUS <hi>the Son.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Publius,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">U.C. <hi>447.</hi>
                     </note> the Son of the former <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cius,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Before Ch. <hi>303.</hi>
                     </note> in his firſt Conſulſhip triumphed over the <hi>Samnites,</hi> and conſecrated the beſt of their Spoils to <hi>Ceres:</hi> in his ſecond and third Conſulate he per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd many noble Actions both at home and abroad. In his fourth with <hi>Fabius Maximus Rullianus,</hi> when the <hi>Gauls,</hi> the <hi>Samnites,</hi> the <hi>Umbri</hi> and the <hi>Tuſci</hi> enter'd into a Confederacy a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Romans,</hi> their Army being drawn up in Battel, and in the Fight his Wing giving ground, he, encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:99029:33"/>by the great Example of his Father, ſent for <hi>Marcus Livius</hi> the <hi>Pontifex,</hi> and leaning on his Spear, repeated after him the uſual Form of Prayer, thus devoting himſelf toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the Enemy to the Infernal Gods, he ruſhed into the Battel, and bequeathed Victory to his Soldiers. His Body was magnificently interred, and he prais'd in a Funeral Oration by his Colleague.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="biography">
                  <head>TITUS MANLIUS TOR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>QUATUS.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Titus Manlius Torquatus,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">U.C. <hi>395.</hi>
                     </note> for the Dulneſs of his Parts, and the Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diment of his Speech,<note place="margin">Before Ch. <hi>355.</hi>
                     </note> was ſent by his Father to live a private Life in the Country; upon Information that his Father was accuſed by <hi>Pompeius,</hi> the Tribune of the People, he came by night to <hi>Rome,</hi> and having got an opportunity to diſcourſe the Tribune in private, with his drawn Sword, forc'd him in great fear to lay aſide his Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſation. In his Tribuneſhip of the
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:99029:34"/>Soldiers, under <hi>Sulpicius</hi> the Dictator, he in a Duel kill'd the <hi>Gaul</hi> that chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leng'd the <hi>Romans,</hi> and taking off his Chain, put it on his own Neck, whence he as call'd <hi>Terquatus.</hi> In his Conſulſhip againſt the <hi>Latins,</hi> to maintain his Diſcipline, he beheaded his own Son, tho victorious, for fighting againſt his Order, and beat them at the River <hi>Veſeris,</hi> where his Colleague <hi>Decius</hi> devoted himſelf to the Infernal Gods.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="biography">
                  <head>MARCUS VALERIUS COR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VINUS.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">U.C. <hi>407.</hi>
                     </note>
                     <hi>Valerius</hi> was Tribune of the Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers under <hi>Camillus,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Before Ch. <hi>343.</hi>
                     </note> in purſuing the diſperſt Troops of the <hi>Gauls</hi> out of <hi>Italy;</hi> and with great Bravery fought the <hi>Gaul,</hi> who by a Challenge had ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified the whole <hi>Roman</hi> Army. A Crow from Break of Day ſate upon his Hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met, and in the Fight aſſiſted him by flapping his Wing in his Enemies Eyes, which Victory honoured him
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:99029:34"/>with the additional Name of <hi>Corvinus.</hi> His Prudence was of great Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence to the Common-Wealth, when a great number of poor Debtors, not able to pay their Creditors, had at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted to ſeize <hi>Capua,</hi> and forc'd <hi>Quinctius</hi> to head them, in appeaſing that Sedition by taking off the Debt.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="biography">
                  <head>SPURIUS POSTHUMIUS.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">U.C. <hi>433.</hi>
                     </note>
                     <hi>Titus Veturius</hi> and <hi>Spurius Posthumius</hi> in their Conſulſhip warring with the <hi>Samnites,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Before Ch. <hi>317.</hi>
                     </note> were drawn into an Ambu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcade by their General <hi>Pontius Thele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinus,</hi> who ſent out ſome pretended Deſerters to tell the <hi>Romans,</hi> that <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceria,</hi> a City in <hi>Apulia,</hi> was beſieg'd by the <hi>Samnites.</hi> Two Roads lead to this place, the one longer, but ſafer; the other ſhorter, yet more dangerous; the <hi>Romans;</hi> in great haſte to raiſe the Seige, by taking the ſhorter way, fell into the Ambuſh: the place, where this Misfortune happen'd, was call'd <hi>Furcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lae Caudinae. Caius Pontius,</hi> when he
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:99029:35"/>had taken them, ſent for his Father <hi>Herennius,</hi> to conſult his Judgment in this matter, who anſwer'd, He would either have them all killed, to weaken their Forces beyond hopes of Recovery, or elſe ſent away without Ranſom, that they might be for ever oblig'd to him for ſuch a generous Favour; but he rejecting both theſe Propoſitions, made them all Slaves, and enter'd into a League with diſhonourable Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions on their part, which the <hi>Romans</hi> ſo diſliked, that <hi>Poſthumius</hi> their Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral was deliver'd up to them to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>annul the Articles, but not received upon that Account by them.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="biography">
                  <head>LUCIUS PAPIRIUS CUR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SOR.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Lucius Papirius,</hi> from his ſwiftneſs call'd <hi>Curſor,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">U.C. <hi>434.</hi>
                     </note> was ſent Dictator againſt the <hi>Samnites,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Before Ch. <hi>316.</hi>
                     </note> perceiving the War to be undertook with ill Omens, he return'd to <hi>Rome</hi> to conſult the Soothſayers for better Divination, and left the Command
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:99029:35"/>of the Army to <hi>Fabius Rullianus,</hi> with Orders not to fight upon any Occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, yet he inticed by a fair Oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity fought the Enemy, for which <hi>Papirius,</hi> at his return, would have beheaded him. For the ſafety of his life he eſcaped to <hi>Rome,</hi> where it was not in the Power of the Tribunes to defend him: nevertheleſs by his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Tears, and the Peoples Intreaty, he was at laſt pardoned, and <hi>Papirius</hi> triumph'd over the <hi>Samnites.</hi> He was very pleaſant in his Converſation, and a great Lover of Jeſts, as appear'd one time, after having ſeverely repri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded the Praetor of <hi>Praeneſte</hi> for his Cowardiſe, he order'd the Lictors to make ready their Axes; and when he ſaw him ſufficiently terrified with the fear of Death, commanded them only to cut up the Roots that hinder'd their March.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="Bertie" type="translator">
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:99029:36"/>
               <head>The HONORABLE Mr. <hi>ROBERT BERTIE.</hi> From the Year 434. to 511. <hi>U.C.</hi>
               </head>
               <div type="biography">
                  <head>QUINCTUS FABIUS RULLIANUS.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">U.C. <hi>434.</hi>
                     </note>Q. <hi>Fabius Rullianus</hi> was the firſt of his Family,<note place="margin">Before Ch. <hi>316.</hi>
                     </note> for his Valour call'd <hi>Maximus:</hi> when he was General of the Horſe, under <hi>Papirius Curſor,</hi> he conquer'd the <hi>Samnites,</hi> but had like to have been beheaded by the Dicta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, for fighting without Order, in his abſence. He firſt triumph'd over the <hi>Apuli,</hi> and <hi>Lucerini,</hi> then over the <hi>Samnites;</hi> thirdly over the <hi>Gauls,</hi> the <hi>Umbri,</hi> the <hi>Marſi,</hi> and the <hi>Tuſci.</hi> In his Cenſorſhip he diſtinguiſh'd the <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertini,</hi> in reſpect of their Votes, into
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:99029:36"/>four inferior Tribes, and would not be choſe Cenſor a ſecond time, declaring it was not for the good of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth to have the ſame Men of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten Cenſors. He firſt inſtituted the Cavalcade of the <hi>Roman</hi> Knights on the Ides of <hi>July</hi> from the Temple of Honor, upon white Horſes to the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitol. At his death ſo much Money was collected for him by publick Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribution, that his Son made a pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Feaſt, and gave a Dole of raw Fleſh to the People.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="biography">
                  <head>MANLIUS CURIUS DEN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TATUS.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">U.C. <hi>404.</hi>
                     </note>
                     <hi>Manlius Curius Dentatus</hi> firſt tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph'd over the <hi>Samnites,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Before Ch. <hi>446.</hi>
                     </note> whom he conquer'd as far as the <hi>Adriatick</hi> Sea. At his return to <hi>Rome,</hi> he thus ſigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liz'd the Greatneſs of his Victory in an Affembly of the People: <hi>I hvae taken ſo much Land, that it would turn a Deſart, had I not taken ſo many Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners to inhabit it; and have taken ſo
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:99029:37"/>many Men, that they muſt periſh with Hunger, had I not taken ſo much Ground for them to ſubſiſt on.</hi> He triumph'd a ſecond time over the <hi>Sabines,</hi> and thirdly enter'd the City with a leſs Triumph, call'd Ovation, for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quering the <hi>Lucanians.</hi> He drove <hi>Pyrrhus,</hi> King of <hi>Epirus,</hi> out of <hi>Italy.</hi> In the Diviſion of the publick Lands, he gave forty Acres a Man amongſt the People, and reſerv'd but forty for himſelf, profeſſing, that none ought to be reckon'd a <hi>Roman</hi> Citizen who could not be contented with it. He was ſo moderate in his Deſires, that he anſwer'd the <hi>Samnite</hi> Embaſſadors, proffering him a great Preſent of Gold, as he was at Dinner upon roaſted Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nips; <hi>I had rather eat theſe Turnips in this Earthen Diſh, and govern them that poſſeſs ſuch Riches.</hi> When he was ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus'd of converting to his own uſe the publick Money, he produced for his Vindication a Wooden Cruet which he us'd at his Sacrifices, ſolemnly ſwear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, he never had any thing more of the Enemies Spoils, in his Houſe. He
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:99029:37"/>brought the Aqueducts of the River <hi>Anio</hi> into <hi>Rome,</hi> at the Expence of the ſame Plunder; and in his Tribune<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip forced the Senate to make the Law from him, call'd <hi>Curia,</hi> by which Magiſtrates might be elected out of the Plebeians; for which many Obligations the Republick conferr'd upon him an Houſe, and five hundred Acres of Land in <hi>Tiphata.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="biography">
                  <head>APPIUS CLAUDIUS CAECUS.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Appius Claudius Caecus,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">U.C. <hi>462.</hi>
                     </note> in his Cenſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip,<note place="margin">Before Ch. <hi>288.</hi>
                     </note> tho he admitted the <hi>Libertini</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Senate, prohibited the Muſici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans from publick Feaſting, and play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on Pipes in <hi>Jupiter</hi>'s Temple Two Families call'd the <hi>Potitii</hi> and the <hi>Pinarii</hi> had for many Ages been con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted to perform Sacrifices to <hi>Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cules,</hi> he brib'd the <hi>Potitii</hi> to inſtruct the common Slaves in thoſe Religious Ceremonies, for which Offence he was ſtruck blind, and the Race of the <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titii</hi> utterly extinguiſh'd. He violent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:99029:38"/>oppos'd the Communication of the Conſulſhip to any Plebeian, and would not gratifie the Ambition of <hi>Fabius Rullianus</hi> to have abſolute Command without <hi>Decius Mus</hi> in the War againſt the <hi>Samnites.</hi> He conquer'd the <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bines, Samnites,</hi> and <hi>Hetrurians:</hi> and pav'd the way as far as <hi>Brunduſium,</hi> whence it was call'd the <hi>Appian</hi> Road. He finiſh'd the Aqueduct which was brought into <hi>Rome</hi> from the River <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nio,</hi> and was the only Man that kept the Cenſorſhip five years toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. When a Peace was concluding with King <hi>Pyrrhus,</hi> and his Embaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor <hi>Cineas</hi> had corrupted many of the Senators, <hi>Appius,</hi> old and blind, was brought in his Litter into the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, and with a noble Speech broke off thoſe baſe Propoſitions.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="biography">
                  <head>PYRRHUS <hi>King of</hi> Epirus.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Pyrrhus,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">U.C. <hi>472.</hi>
                     </note> King of <hi>Epirus,</hi> was by his Father deſcended from <hi>Achilles;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Before Ch. <hi>278.</hi>
                     </note> by his Mother from <hi>Hercules;</hi> he ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiouſly
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:99029:38"/>aimed at the Empire of the World, and perceiving the <hi>Romans</hi> very powerful, conſulted the <hi>Del<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phick</hi> Oracle about the Fortune of the War, whom <hi>Apollo</hi> thus ambiguouſly anſwer'd:
<q>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Aio te Aeacida Romanos vincere poſſe.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>O, Pyrrhus, <hi>you the</hi> Romans <hi>ſhall o'ercome.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </q>
He interpreting this to his own Fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, made War with the <hi>Romans,</hi> by the help of the <hi>Tarentini:</hi> and diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd <hi>Laevinus</hi> the Conſul's Army by the City <hi>Heraclea,</hi> with the ſtrange ſight of his Elephants; but after the Fight when he beheld the <hi>Roman</hi> Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, ſlain only by honourable Wounds in their Breaſts; he cried out, <hi>With ſuch brave Men as theſe could I ſoon conquer the whole World:</hi> and anſwer'd his Friends, congratulating his Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs, <hi>What do I gain by ſuch a Victory as coſts me the Flower of my Army.</hi> Then he march'd on, and encamp'd
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:99029:39"/>twenty Miles from <hi>Rome,</hi> generouſly reſtoring the Captives to <hi>Fabricius,</hi> without Ranſom, where ſeeing the new Army of <hi>Laevinus</hi> ſo ſuddenly recruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, he declar'd he underwent the ſame Difficulty againſt the <hi>Romans,</hi> as his Anceſtor <hi>Hercules</hi> with the Serpent <hi>Hydra.</hi> He was routed by <hi>Fabricius</hi> and <hi>Curius,</hi> and fled to <hi>Tarentum,</hi> thence paſs'd over into <hi>Sicily,</hi> yet once more to try his Fortune, he return'd to <hi>Locri</hi> in <hi>Italy,</hi> and rob'd <hi>Proſerpine</hi>'s Temple; but en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavouring to carry off the Treaſure, his Fleet was driven back by a Storm, and wreck'd upon the Shoar. Thence returning into <hi>Greece,</hi> as he beſieg'd <hi>Argos,</hi> he was ſlain with a Tile thrown down on his Head. His Body was carried to <hi>Antigonus,</hi> King of <hi>Macedo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia,</hi> and magnificently enterr'd.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="biography">
                  <head>FABRICIUS.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">U.C. <hi>477.</hi>
                     </note>The year after the victorious <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans</hi> had driven <hi>Pyrrhus</hi> to <hi>Tarentum Fabricius</hi> was ſent General againſt<note place="margin">Before Ch. <hi>273.</hi>
                     </note>
                     <pb n="55" facs="tcp:99029:39"/>him; he had been formerly Embaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor to <hi>Pyrrhus,</hi> and tho he was prof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd a fourth part of his Kingdom, would not be brid'd from his Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſty. When he and the King en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>camp'd near one another, <hi>Pyrrhus</hi>'s Phyſician came to him by night, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſing to poiſon his Prince, if he would reward him accordingly; <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bricius,</hi> deteſting the Fact, command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him to be bound, and carried back, that his Lord might know what this Traitor had deſign'd againſt his Life. In admiration of which generous Action the King is reported to have ſaid; <hi>This is that</hi> Fabricius, <hi>whoſe In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegrity 'tis harder to corrupt, than to turn the Sun from its Courſe.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="biography">
                  <head>DECIUS MUS.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Volſcinii,</hi> a noble City of <hi>Hetruria,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">U.C. <hi>487.</hi>
                     </note> was almoſt ruin'd by its Luxury;<note place="margin">Before Ch. <hi>263.</hi>
                     </note> for very indiſcreetly they had freed their Slaves, and admitted them into the Senate, who in return, by a Confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racy,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:99029:40"/>became their Maſters. After they had thus ſuffer'd many Indignities they ſecretly begg'd Aid of the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans; Decius Mus</hi> was preſently ſent to their Aſſiſtance, who overcame theſe inſolent Freed Men, and either put them to Death in Priſon, or delivered them again in ſubjection to their Lords.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="biography">
                  <head>APPIUS CLAUDIUS CAU<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DEX.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Appius Claudius,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">U.C. <hi>488.</hi>
                     </note> ſirnamed <hi>Caudex,</hi> was Brother to <hi>Appius Caecus,</hi> after the Settlement of the <hi>Volſinienſes,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Before Ch. <hi>262.</hi>
                     </note> he was ſent Conſul to free the <hi>Mamertini</hi> in <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cily,</hi> whoſe Caſtle <hi>Hiero,</hi> King of <hi>Syracuſe,</hi> with the <hi>Carthaginians,</hi> had beſieg'd. He firſt paſs'd the Streights of <hi>Sicily</hi> in a Fiſher-Boat to view the Enemy, and the forc'd the <hi>Carthaginian</hi> Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral to withdraw his Forces out of the Cittadel. Returning to <hi>Rhegium,</hi> he with his Infantry took a five Bank'd Galley of the Enemies, and with that Veſſel tranſporting a Legion into <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cily,</hi>
                     <pb n="57" facs="tcp:99029:40"/>drove the <hi>Carthaginians</hi> from <hi>Meſſana. Hiero</hi> ſurrendered himſelf to him upon Terms, at the Battel of <hi>Syracuſe,</hi> and was ſo terrified with the Danger of the War, that he deſir'd the Friendſhip of the <hi>Romans,</hi> and prov'd ever after very faithful to them.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="biography">
                  <head>CAIUS DUILIUS.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">U.C. <hi>258.</hi>
                     </note>
                     <hi>Caius Duilius</hi> was Admiral in the firſt <hi>Punick</hi> War againſt the <hi>Carthagini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Before Ch. <hi>492.</hi>
                     </note> and finding them very powerful at Sea, rigg'd out a ſtrong Fleet: his Enemies laugh'd at his Invention of Grapling Irons, with which he took thirty, and ſunk thirteen of their Ships. <hi>Hannibal,</hi> the <hi>Carthaginian</hi> Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miral, fled to <hi>Carthage,</hi> and pretended to demand Inſtructions of the Senate, as yet ignorant of his Misfortune. They unanimouſly voted he ſhould fight the Enemy: <hi>I have fought,</hi> ſays he, <hi>and loſt the Day.</hi> Thus he eſcap'd Crucifixion; for among the <hi>Carthagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians,</hi> the General, that had the Mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortune
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:99029:41"/>fortune to be beaten, was ſo puniſh'd. <hi>Dailius</hi> had this perpetual Honor con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fen'd on him, to return in publick from Supper with Flambeaux and Trumpeters before him.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="biography">
                  <head>ATILIUS CALATINUS.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Atilius Calatinus</hi> was ſent General into <hi>Sicily</hi> againſt the <hi>Carthaginians,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">U.C. <hi>494.</hi>
                     </note> he forced the Enemies Garriſons out of <hi>Enna,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Before Ch. <hi>256.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Drepanum,</hi> and <hi>Lilybaeum,</hi> their beſt and ſtrongeſt Cities, and took <hi>Panormus.</hi> He ravag'd the whole Iſland, and with a few Ships, beat the Enemies great Fleet, under the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of <hi>Amilcar.</hi> But making haſte to raiſe the Siege of <hi>Camerina,</hi> he was ſhut up in a narrow Paſs by the <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thaginians,</hi> where <hi>Calpurnius Flamma,</hi> one of his Tribunes, drawing out three hundred Soldiers, gain'd a Hill, and by his Valour freed the Conſul, tho his whole Party was cut off, and he found half dead by the Conſul:
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:99029:41"/>After this the <hi>Romans</hi> became a Terror to their Enemies, and <hi>Atilius</hi> obtain'd a Glorious Triumph.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="biography">
                  <head>MARCUS ATILIUS RE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>GULUS.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>M. Atilius Regulus</hi> in his Conſulſhip<note place="margin">U.C. <hi>497.</hi>
                     </note> triumph'd for his Conqueſt over the <hi>Salentini:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Before Ch. <hi>253.</hi>
                     </note> he was the firſt <hi>Roman</hi> Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral that paſs'd over with a Navy in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Africa:</hi> his Fleet ſuffer'd much by a Shipwreck: yet he took from <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milcar,</hi> the <hi>Carthaginian</hi> Admiral, ſixty three Gallies, beſides two hundred Towns, with two hundred thouſand Captives. Whilſt he commanded a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad, his Wife and Children, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of their Poverty, were kept at the Publick Charge. The next year he was taken by the policy of <hi>Xanthippus,</hi> a <hi>Lacedaemonian</hi> Captain, who ſerv'd the <hi>Carthaginians,</hi> and caſt into Priſon. He was ſent Embaſſador from thence to <hi>Rome,</hi> to treat about the Exchange of Priſoners, promiſing, upon his
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:99029:42"/>Oath, to return, if he could not ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain it; but he more conſulting the Benefit of his Country, oppos'd it in the Senate, and not regarding the Prayers and Tears of his Wife and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily, returned to <hi>Carthage,</hi> where, in revenge, they put him into a Wooden Cheſt, ſtuck full of Nails, by which horrible Torture, and for want of Sleep he died.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="biography">
                  <head>CAIUS LUTATIUS CATU<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LUS.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>C. Lutatius Catulus,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">U.C. <hi>511.</hi>
                     </note> in the firſt <hi>Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nick</hi> War commanded three hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Sail againſt the <hi>Carthaginians,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Before Ch. <hi>239.</hi>
                     </note> and in a Fight near the Iſlands <hi>Aegates,</hi> between <hi>Sicily</hi> and <hi>Africa,</hi> took and and ſunk ſix hundred of their Ships, laden with Proviſions and other Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſaries, under their Admiral <hi>Anno,</hi> by which great Victory he put an end to the War; and at their Entreaty made a Peace with them on theſe Terms, that they ſhould march out of
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:99029:42"/>
                     <hi>Sicily, Sardinia,</hi> and the other Iſlands between <hi>Italy,</hi> and <hi>Africa;</hi> giving up all Provinces in <hi>Spain,</hi> as far as the River <hi>Iberus.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="Parkyns" type="translator">
               <head>Mr. <hi>BLAKWELL PARKYNS.</hi> From the Year 511. to 563. <hi>U.C.</hi>
               </head>
               <div type="biography">
                  <head>HANNIBAL the <hi>Carthaginian</hi> General.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>HAnnibal</hi> was Son to <hi>Hamilcar,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">U.C. <hi>534.</hi>
                     </note> General of the <hi>Carthaginians,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Before Ch. <hi>216.</hi>
                     </note> in the firſt <hi>Punick</hi> War, who brought him, when but nine years old, before the Altar, ſolemnly to ſwear perpetual Hatred to <hi>Rome.</hi> From that time he ſerved in thoſe Wars under his Father, after whoſe Death he ſought all Occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:99029:43"/>of Breaking with the <hi>Romans.</hi> To which end, he, within ſix Months after, deſtroyed the City <hi>Saguntum</hi> in <hi>Spain,</hi> then in Confederacy with them. From whence making his Way over the <hi>Alpes,</hi> he paſſed into <hi>Italy,</hi> and beat <hi>Publius Scipio</hi> at <hi>Ticinum; Sempro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius Longus</hi> at <hi>Trebia; Flaminius</hi> at the Lake <hi>Traſimenus;</hi> alſo <hi>Paulus</hi> and <hi>Varro</hi> at <hi>Cannae.</hi> And might further have carried his Victories, by taking <hi>Rome</hi> it ſelf, had he march'd directly thither, and not turn'd aſide into <hi>Campania,</hi> to enjoy the Pleaſures of that rich Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try. But after this, when he had en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>camp'd his Army within three Miles of the City, he was beat back by great Storms of Wind and Rain. His Troops were firſt weakened by <hi>Fabius Maximus;</hi> then repulſed by <hi>Valerius Flaccus;</hi> next put to flight by <hi>Gracchus</hi> and <hi>Marcellus;</hi> and being recalled into <hi>Africa,</hi> he was there totally routed by <hi>Scipio.</hi> From thence he fled to <hi>Antio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chus,</hi> King of <hi>Syria,</hi> and incited him to make War againſt the <hi>Romans;</hi> after whoſe Overthrow, he was neceſſitated
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:99029:43"/>to retire to <hi>Pruſias,</hi> King of <hi>Bythinia,</hi> to whom <hi>Titus Flaminius</hi> was ſent on an Embaſſy to demand him; but he prevented his being deliver'd up by drinking a Poiſon, carried for ſuch an Occaſion, in the hollow of his Ring, and ſo died. At <hi>Lybiſſa,</hi> a Town of <hi>Bythinia</hi> he was put into a Stone Coffin, with this Inſcription on it,</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Here lies</hi> HANNIBAL.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="biography">
                  <head>Q. FABIUS MAXIMUS.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Quintus Fabius Maximus Cunctator</hi> was called <hi>Verrucoſus,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">U.C. <hi>535.</hi>
                     </note> from a Wart he had on his Lip; and <hi>Ovicula,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Before Ch. <hi>215.</hi>
                     </note> from his mild Nature. In his Conſulſhip he triumph'd over the <hi>Ligures,</hi> and weak'ned <hi>Hannibal</hi> by his prudent De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laying to give him Battle. He ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Minutius,</hi> General of his Horſe, at his Requeſt, to have equal Power in the Army with himſelf; yet after that Arrogance, refuſed not to relieve him, when he had brought his Troops by ill
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:99029:44"/>Conduct into great Danger. He ſhut up <hi>Hannibal</hi> in the Plains of <hi>Falernus,</hi> and kept <hi>Manlius Statilius</hi> from revolt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Enemy, by his generous gift to him of a Horſe and Arms; alſo obliged a brave Soldier of the <hi>Lucani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> Squadron, who often left the Camp, and neglected his Duty, being tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſported with a violent Paſſion for a beautiful Woman, by buying and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting her to him. He retook <hi>Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentum</hi> from the <hi>Carthaginians,</hi> and the Statue of <hi>Hercules,</hi> which he brought from thence, he placed in the Capitol. And when the Senate would not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove of his Ratifying the Articles, made between him and the Enemy, about the Redemption of Priſoners, he ſold his Eſtate for two hundred thouſand Seſterces, with which he preſerved his Honour, and performed his Contract.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="biography">
                  <pb n="65" facs="tcp:99029:44"/>
                  <head>PUBLIUS SCIPIO NASICA.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Publius Scipio Naſica</hi> was a Man ſo eminent for his Virtue, that he had the Image of <hi>Cybele,</hi> Mother of the Gods, by order of the Senate, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to his Care, to be kept in his Houſe, till her Temple ſhould be built. He was ſo ſuperſtitious, that when he underſtood himſelf to be choſen Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſul by <hi>Gracchus</hi> with ill Omens, he ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicated his Office. In his Cenſorſhip he pulled down the Statues, which many, out of Ambition, had erected for themſelves in the <hi>Forum.</hi> And in his Conſulſhip took <hi>Delminium,</hi> chief City of the <hi>Calmatians.</hi> Out of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſty he refuſed the Title of General, offered him by the Soldiers, as he did the Honour of a Triumph conferred on him by the Senate. He was ſo ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry eloquent, ſo well skilled in the Law, and ſo extremely wiſe in all his Affairs, that he was called <hi>Corculum,</hi> or <hi>The Prudent Man.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="biography">
                  <pb n="66" facs="tcp:99029:45"/>
                  <head>M. CLAUDIUS MARCELLUS.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Marcus Marcellus</hi> ſlew <hi>Virdumarus,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>U.C.</hi> 530.</note> Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral of the <hi>Gauls,</hi> in a ſingle Combat,<note place="margin">Before Ch. <hi>220.</hi>
                     </note> and was the Third from <hi>Romulus</hi> that dedicated the rich Spoils of a ſlain Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral to <hi>Jupiter Feretrius.</hi> He firſt taught Soldiers to retreat without turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their Backs, and by taking Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of a narrow Paſs at <hi>Nola,</hi> made <hi>Hannibal</hi> know, he was not invincible. <hi>Syracuſe,</hi> a City in <hi>Sicily,</hi> was taken by him after three years Siege, and when the Senate, upon ſome falſe Accuſation denied him the Honour of a Triumph, he conſcious of his juſt merit triumph'd from his own Authority on Mount <hi>Alban.</hi> In his fifth Conſulſhip he was unluckily drawn into an Ambuſcade, by <hi>Hannibal,</hi> and ſlain. His Funeral was ſolemnized with great Pomp; but his Bones, as they were ſent to <hi>Rome,</hi> were intercepted by <hi>Numidian</hi> Pyrats, and loſt.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="biography">
                  <pb n="67" facs="tcp:99029:45"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>LIVIA CLAUDIA</hi> the Veſtal Virgin.</head>
                  <p>Whilſt <hi>Hannibal</hi> waſted <hi>Italy,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>U.C</hi> 549.</note> the <hi>Romans</hi> conſulting the Books of the <hi>Sybils,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Before Ch. <hi>201.</hi>
                     </note> ſent for the Image of the God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſs <hi>Cybele</hi> from <hi>Peſſinuns,</hi> a Town of <hi>Phrygia.</hi> And as they came up the <hi>Tiber</hi> againſt the Stream, the Ship on a ſudden ſtopp'd in deep Water, from whence it could by no Means be moved, till by Direction in the ſame Books, they underſtood that it might be drawn up the River by the Hand of a very chaſte Woman. Whereupon <hi>Claudia,</hi> a Veſtal Virgin, unjuſtly ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpected of Incontinency, entreated the Goddeſs, that if ſhe knew her to be chaſte, ſhe would vouchſafe to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low her, then tying her Girdle to the Ship, ſhe drew it up the <hi>Tiber.</hi> The Image of the Goddeſs, whilſt her Temple was building, was placed in the Houſe of <hi>Scipio Naſica,</hi> ſo honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red from the general Opinion of being the beſt Man in <hi>Rome.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="biography">
                  <pb n="68" facs="tcp:99029:46"/>
                  <head>M. PORCIUS CATO CEN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SORIUS.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>M. Porcius Cato</hi> was born at <hi>Tuſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>U.C.</hi> 557.</note> but invited to fix at <hi>Rome,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Before Ch. <hi>193.</hi>
                     </note> by <hi>Valerius Flaccus.</hi> He was Tribune of the Soldiers in <hi>Sicily;</hi> and behaved himſelf with great Valour whileſt he was Queſtor under <hi>Scipio,</hi> as he did with great Juſtice, when Pretor. In that year of his Pretorſhip he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer'd <hi>Sardinia,</hi> and was there in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed in the <hi>Greek</hi> Tongue by <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius</hi> the Poet. In his Conſulſhip he <hi>Hiſpania Tarraconenſis;</hi> and to ſecure them from rebelling, he ſent his Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders to all the Cities to demoliſh their Walls, which every one of them ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gining as only ſent to them in parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular, readily obeyed. In the <hi>Syrian</hi> War againſt <hi>Antiochus,</hi> being Tribune of the Soldiers, under <hi>Marcus Acilius Glabrio,</hi> he gained the Paſs of <hi>Thermo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pylae,</hi> at the Streights of Mount <hi>Oeta,</hi> and by that prevention routed the
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:99029:46"/>Enemy. In his Cenſorſhip he turned <hi>Lucius Flammius,</hi> who formerly had been Conſul, out of the Senate, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe in his Government of <hi>Gaul,</hi> to pleaſe his Miſs, he ordered a Captive to be brought out of Priſon, and killed before her. He was the firſt that built a ſtately Piazza, calling it <hi>Porcia,</hi> after his own Name, and oppoſed the Luxu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the <hi>Roman</hi> Matrons, when they demanded the Privilege of wearing their rich Ornaments, taken from from them by the <hi>Oppian</hi> Law. He was ſo indefatigable a Proſecutor of ill Men, that in the fourſcorth year of his Age he accuſed <hi>Galba</hi> for rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing the <hi>Lufitanians</hi> in his Pretorſhip, and was himſelf impeached four and forty times, but always honourably acquitted. In the Debates of the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, in the third <hi>Punick</hi> War, he was for demoliſhing <hi>Carthage;</hi> his natural Vigor laſted ſo long, that he had a Son at fourſcore, whoſe Effigies was often brought out to honour a Funeral Solemnity.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="biography">
                  <pb n="70" facs="tcp:99029:47"/>
                  <head>C. CLAUDIUS NERO, <hi>and</hi> ASDRUBAL HANNIBAL's <hi>Brother.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Aſdrubal,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">U.C. <hi>545.</hi>
                     </note> the Brother of <hi>Hannibal,</hi> paſſed into <hi>Italy</hi> with great Recruits,<note place="margin">Before Ch. <hi>205.</hi>
                     </note> for the ſtrengthening his Army, and the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire had then been utterly ruined, if he had once joyned his Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: But <hi>Claudius Nero,</hi> whoſe Camp was in <hi>Apulia</hi> near <hi>Hannibal,</hi> leaving part of his Forces behind him, drew out a large Detachment of his choiceſt Men, and marching directly againſt <hi>Aſdrubal,</hi> joined <hi>M. Livius</hi> his Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>league, at a Town called <hi>Sena,</hi> by the River <hi>Metaurus</hi> in <hi>Calabria,</hi> where they two together beat <hi>Aſdrubal.</hi> After this Victory <hi>Nero</hi> returned to his Camp with the ſame ſpeed, and threw <hi>Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drubal</hi>'s Head before his Brother <hi>Han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibal</hi>'s Trenches. At which ſight <hi>Han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibal</hi> publickly declared, he was over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come by the ill Fortune of <hi>Carthage.</hi> For this good Service <hi>Marcus Livius</hi>
                     <pb n="71" facs="tcp:99029:47"/>entered <hi>Rome</hi> with a greater Triumph, and, <hi>Nero</hi> with a leſs, becauſe the Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on was not performed within his Province.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="biography">
                  <head>P. CORNELIUS SCIPIO.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Publius Scipio,</hi> called <hi>Africanus,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">U.C. <hi>551.</hi>
                     </note> for his Courage and Conduct in the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt of <hi>Africa,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Before Ch. <hi>199.</hi>
                     </note> was ſuppoſed to be the Son of <hi>Jupiter,</hi> for before his Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was with Child of him, a Serpent, ſuppoſed the Genius of <hi>Jupiter,</hi> was ſeen in her Bed, and in his Childhood a Snake twined about him without do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him any harm. The Dogs never bark'd at him, altho he went into the Capitol at Midnight, nor did he ever undertake any Buſineſs, till he had ſate meditating a good while, near the Image of <hi>Jupiter,</hi> as if he received Directions from that God. He but eighteen years of Age, by his ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular Valour, ſaved his Father's Life at <hi>Ticinum;</hi> and ſo great Influence was the Authority of <hi>Scipio,</hi> that he put a ſtop to the young Noblemen, and
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:99029:48"/>hinder'd them from leaving <hi>Italy,</hi> and conducted the Remainder of the Army, after the Defeat of <hi>Cannae,</hi> through the Enemies Camp to <hi>Canuſium.</hi> At four and twenty he was ſent Pretor in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Spain,</hi> and took <hi>Carthago Nova,</hi> now <hi>Carthagena,</hi> the ſame day he came be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it, when his Soldiers brought him a young Maid, whoſe Beauty attract<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed every one to be a Spectator, he out of Modeſty would not ſee her, but gave order, that ſhe ſhould be reſtored to her Father, and betrothed Lover, a Prince of <hi>Cel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>iberia.</hi> He beat <hi>Aſdrubal</hi> and <hi>Mage, Hannibal</hi>'s Brothers, out of <hi>Spain,</hi> made a League with <hi>Syphax,</hi> King of <hi>Mauritania,</hi> and received <hi>Maſſaniſſa</hi> into the Number of the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies. Returning home after theſe Victories, he was made Conſul before he was old enough, according to Law, and by the Conſent of his Colleague paſſed over into <hi>Africa,</hi> and forc'd his way through <hi>Aſdrubal</hi>'s and <hi>Syphax</hi>'s Camp in one night. He vanquiſhed <hi>Hannibal</hi> after he was recalled out of <hi>Italy,</hi> and impoſed new Laws upon
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:99029:48"/>the conquered <hi>Carthaginians,</hi> In the War againſt <hi>Antiochus</hi> he was his Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther's Lieutenant, and his Son that was taken Priſoner was returned with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Ranſom, in honour of the Father. Being accuſed of Extortion by the <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilii,</hi> and <hi>Naevius,</hi> Tribunes of the People, with great aſſurance, he tore his Book of Accounts in pieces, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the People, and ſaid, <hi>This day I conquered</hi> Carthage; <hi>'twas a good piece of Service to the Commonwealth, let us go to the Capitol, and return our publick Thanks to the Gods.</hi> Then he left the ungrateful City, ſpending the reſt of his Life in exile; and at his death beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged of his Wife, that his Body ſhould not be carried back to <hi>Rome.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="biography">
                  <head>MARCUS LIVIUS SALINA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TOR.</head>
                  <p>In his firſt Conſulſhip triumph'd over the <hi>Illyrians,</hi> yet ſometime after was maliciouſly accuſed by all the Tribes, except the <hi>Metian,</hi> for em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bezelling
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:99029:49"/>the publick Stock. In his ſecond Conſulſhip he was joined with his Enemy <hi>Claudius Nero,</hi> but rather than the Government ſhould ſuſtain any prejudice from their Variance, he was freely reconciled to him, and upon their Victory over <hi>Aſdrubal, Hannibal</hi>'s Brother, rode in Triumph into the City. He was alſo choſe with the ſame <hi>Nero</hi> in his Cenſorſhip, and ſet a Poll-Tax upon every Tribe, except the <hi>Metians,</hi> taking away their Penſion, becauſe they had either con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned very unjuſtly at firſt, or elſe had done very ill, in conferring ſo great Honours upon him, after a for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer ſuſpicion.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="biography">
                  <head>TITUS QUINCTIUS FLAMINIUS.</head>
                  <p>Was the Son of that <hi>Flaminius</hi> who who was killed at <hi>Traſimenus.</hi> He was ſent Conſul into <hi>Macedonia,</hi> and guided by King <hi>Carops</hi>'s Shepherds into the Province. He routed King <hi>Philip,</hi>
                     <pb n="75" facs="tcp:99029:49"/>and took his Camp, receiving from him his Son <hi>Demetrius</hi> for an Hoſtage, tho afterwards he made him pay a great Ranſom before he reſtored him to his Kingdom. He took alſo the Son of <hi>Nabis,</hi> King of <hi>Lacedemon,</hi> as a Pledge for his Fidelity, and at laſt made Proclamation by the common Cryer at the <hi>Nemaean</hi> Games with ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Applauſe, that all the <hi>Graecians</hi> ſhould enjoy their ancient Liberties. This was he that was ſent to <hi>Pruſias</hi> to demand <hi>Hannibal.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="biography">
                  <head>MARCUS FULVIUS NOBILIOR,</head>
                  <p>In his Pretorſhip conquered <hi>Spain,</hi> for which good Service he enter'd the City, with a leſs Triumph, called <hi>Ovation.</hi> The <hi>Aetolians</hi> and <hi>Ambracians</hi> were routed by him in ſeveral Battels, who in the <hi>Macedonian</hi> War had firſt ſided with the <hi>Romans,</hi> but afterwards revolted to <hi>Antiochus,</hi> King of <hi>Syria.</hi> He drave them into their City <hi>Ambra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cia,</hi>
                     <pb n="76" facs="tcp:99029:50"/>and by a Blockade forced them to ſurrender, yet he plunder'd them of nothing but their Statues, and Pictures, which were carried before him in Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph. His Friend <hi>Quintus Ennius</hi> wrote a noble Poem in commendation of this Victory, tho it was ſufficiently famous of it ſelf, and needed not the Art of a Poet to ſet it off.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="D'Avenant" type="translator">
               <pb n="77" facs="tcp:99029:50"/>
               <head>Mr. <hi>HEARY MOLINS D'AVENANT.</hi> From the Year 563, to 660. <hi>U. C.</hi>
               </head>
               <div type="biography">
                  <head>L. SCIPIO ASIATICUS.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>SCipio Aſiaticus,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">U.C. <hi>563.</hi>
                     </note> Brother to <hi>Scipio Africanus,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Before Ch. <hi>187.</hi>
                     </note> was a Man of a weak Conſtitution, yet upon the Account of his Valour in <hi>Africa,</hi> was recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended by his Brother for Conſul, and having him for his Lieutenant-General, beat <hi>Antiochus,</hi> King of <hi>Syria,</hi> at Mount <hi>Sipylus</hi> in <hi>Caria,</hi> where the Enemies Bows, by reaſon of the exceſſive Rain, were made uſeleſs. He took from him part of his Hereditary Kingdom, and from his Succeſs gained the Name of <hi>Aſiaticus.</hi> Some time after he was ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed for embezelling the Publick Treaſure; but <hi>Gracchus,</hi> Tribune of the
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:99029:51"/>People, ſatisfied of his Integrity, tho his Adverſary, ſtop'd any farther Proceeding, yet <hi>Marcus Cato,</hi> the Cenſor, afterwards took from him his Horſe as a particular Mark of Diſgrace.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="biography">
                  <head>
                     <hi>ANTIOCHUS</hi> King of Syria.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Antiochus,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">U.C. <hi>560.</hi>
                     </note> King of <hi>Syria,</hi> truſting too much to his own Power,<note place="margin">Before Ch. <hi>190.</hi>
                     </note> waged War with the <hi>Romans,</hi> under pretence of recovering the City of <hi>Lyſimachia,</hi> built by his Anceſtors in <hi>Thrace,</hi> and then in the poſſeſſion of the <hi>Romans.</hi> In a ſhort time he ſeized on all <hi>Greece,</hi> with the adjacent Iſlands, but ruined himſelf by Luxury in the Iſland <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boea.</hi> Upon the Approach of <hi>Acilius Glabrio,</hi> he drew up his Forces in the Straits of the Mount <hi>Oeta,</hi> called <hi>Thermopylae,</hi> and after their Defeat, by the Conduct of <hi>Marcus Cato</hi> fled into <hi>Aſia.</hi> He had as bad Succeſs with his Fleet, which under <hi>Hannibal,</hi> his Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miral, was beaten by <hi>Lucius Aemilius,
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:99029:51"/>Regillus,</hi> he thought to oblige <hi>Scipio Africanus,</hi> by releaſing his Son, taken Priſoner at Sea, without any Ranſom, whoſe Father, by way of Requital, adviſed him to make Peace with the <hi>Romans:</hi> but <hi>Antiochus</hi> deſpiſing his Counſel, ventured to fight <hi>L. Scipio</hi> at Mount <hi>Sipylus,</hi> where he was over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come, and chaced beyond Mount <hi>Tau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus.</hi> He was at laſt killed by one of his Nobles, whom he had affronted with a Blow in his Drink.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="biography">
                  <head>CNAEUS MANLIUS VULSO.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Cnaeus Manlius Vulſo,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">U.C. <hi>563.</hi>
                     </note> as ſoon as he was choſen Conſul, was ſent to ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed <hi>Scipio Aſiaticus,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Before Ch. <hi>187.</hi>
                     </note> in his Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and being too ambitious of a Triumph, made War upon the <hi>Piſidae</hi> and <hi>Gallograeci,</hi> Confederates with <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiochus,</hi> whom he very eaſily conquer'd. Amongſt other Priſoners of War, the Wife of King <hi>Orgiagon</hi> was committed to the Charge of a certain Centurion,
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:99029:52"/>who raviſh'd her, but ſhe ſtudying Revenge, conceal'd the Rape; and after ſome time having agreed for her Ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom, by an Artifice had this Adulterer delivered up to her Husband, by whom he was ſlain.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="biography">
                  <head>L. PAULUS AEMILIUS MACEDONICUS.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">U.C. <hi>584.</hi>
                     </note>
                     <hi>L. Paulus Aemilius</hi> was his Son who was ſlain at the Battel of <hi>Cannae.</hi> He in his firſt Conſulſhip,<note place="margin">Before Ch. <hi>166.</hi>
                     </note> which he got after a Repulſe at three Elections, triumph'd over the <hi>Ligures,</hi> and to magnifie his Actions, expoſed to publick view a Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture, wherein all his Exploits were painted. In his ſecond Conſulſhip he took <hi>Perſes,</hi> King of the <hi>Macedonians, Philips</hi> Son, at <hi>Samothracia,</hi> an Iſle in the <hi>Aegean</hi> Sea, but with great Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manity pityed him whom he had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quered, and permitted him to ſit down by him, tho afterward he led him in Triumph. At which joyful Solemnity he loſt two of his Sons, yet
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:99029:52"/>with the greateſt moderation turning himſelf to the People, he made it his requeſt to Fortune, that if any Diſaſter threat'ned the Commonwealth, it might be compounded for, by his private Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions. In reward of his Noble Actions he had the Privilege granted him by the People, and Senate, of wearing a Triumphal Robe at the <hi>Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſian</hi> Games. He was one that ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Avarice, and laid up ſo little Wealth, that after his Death, all his Eſtate was ſold for the Payment of his Wifes Dowry.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="biography">
                  <head>TIB. SEMPRONIUS GRACCHUS.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Tiberius Sempronius Gracchus</hi> was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcended of a Noble Family,<note place="margin">U.C. <hi>573.</hi>
                     </note> and of ſo generous a Temper,<note place="margin">Before Ch. <hi>177.</hi>
                     </note> that he would not ſuffer his Enemy <hi>Scipio Aſiaticus</hi> to be caſt into Priſon. In his Pretor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip he ſubdued <hi>Gaul,</hi> in his firſt Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulſhip <hi>Spain,</hi> and in his ſecond he Conquered <hi>Sardinia,</hi> from whence he
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:99029:53"/>brought ſo many Priſoners, that the long Continuance of their Sale gave occaſion for the Proverb, <hi>Sardi venales, Here are</hi> Sardinian <hi>Slaves to be Sold.</hi> When he was Cenſor he divided thoſe Freemen, who belonged to the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try Tribes, into four City Tribes. Tho he ſecured himſelf by his own Intereſt, yet his Colleague <hi>Claudius</hi> was accuſed for this Innovation, but eſcaped after two Claſſes had found him Guilty, by the zealous Proteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Tiberius,</hi> who vowed, if they condemned his Friend, to be baniſh'd with him. He was a rare Example of Conjugal Affection, when the two Snakes crawled out of his Bed, upon Conſultation the Oracle anſwered, <hi>That if the Male was killed,</hi> Tiberius <hi>ſhould die; if the Female,</hi> Cornelia. Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſs, he moved with a tender compaſſion for his Wife's Safety, or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered he Male to be ſlain.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="biography">
                  <pb n="83" facs="tcp:99029:53"/>
                  <head>PUBLIUS SCIPIO AE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MILIANUS.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>P. Scipio Aemilianus</hi> was the Son of <hi>Paulus Macedonicus,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">U.C. <hi>606.</hi>
                     </note> but adopted by <hi>Scipio Africanus;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Before Ch. <hi>144.</hi>
                     </note> he ſhewed his Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage whilſt he ſerved under his. Father in the <hi>Macedonian</hi> War, upon the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feat of King <hi>Perſes,</hi> by purſuing the Chaſe ſo eagerly, that he did not return to the Camp till Midnight; and when he was <hi>Lucullus</hi>'s Lieutenant in <hi>Spain,</hi> at the Town <hi>Intercatia</hi> he killed one, that challenged him, in a ſingle Combat, and was the firſt that ſcaled the Walls of that City. He was Tribune under <hi>Marcus Manilius,</hi> in the firſt year of the third <hi>Punick</hi> War, and by his Conduct and Valour Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved eight Cohorts, that were block'd up by the Enemy; for which good Service he was preſented with an Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidional Crown. When he ſtood only Candidate for the Aedileſhip, he was unanimouſly choſen Conſul, tho not
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:99029:54"/>of Age, as the Law requires, and within ſix Months, as it were, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm the good Opinion of the People, demoliſh'd <hi>Carthage.</hi> He was then ſent into <hi>Spain,</hi> where having reſtored the Diſcipline of the Army, he forced <hi>Numantia</hi> to Surrender, for want of Proviſions, and was from thence call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Numantinus.</hi> He did nothing with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out his Friend <hi>Caius Laelius,</hi> and in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Embaſſies to ſeveral Princes, took none but him with the ſmall Retinue of two Servants. His noble Exploits at laſt made him ſo haughty, that he diſoblig'd the Commonwealth, by ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Gracchus</hi> was deſervedly Murdered, and when many murmured at this ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere Expreſſion againſt his own Kinſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, he bade them <hi>be ſilent, for ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their Deſerts,</hi> Italy <hi>was but their Stepmother, and they were all no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than his Slaves.</hi> In his Cenſorſhip he Affronted his Colleague <hi>Mummius,</hi> who was indeed a Man of heavy parts, by this arrogant Expreſſion in the open Senate, <hi>I wiſh you had given me a Companion fit for Buſineſs, or none
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:99029:54"/>at all.</hi> Soon after his violent oppoſing the Party which promoted the Diviſion of the Lands, he was found dead at his own Houſe, and carried out to he buried with his Head cover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, leſt there ſhould be any ſuſpicion of a violent Death from the Blackneſs of his Face. His Eſtate was ſo ſmall, that he left but Thirty two Pounds of Silver, and two and a half of Gold.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="biography">
                  <head>CAIUS HOSTILIUS MANCINUS.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">U.C. <hi>615.</hi>
                     </note>
                     <hi>Caius Hoſtilius Mancinus</hi> went Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſul againſt the <hi>Numantines,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Before Ch. <hi>135.</hi>
                     </note> tho fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warn'd by the Augurs, and called upon by a ſtrange Voice to ſtay at home, upon his Arrival at <hi>Numantia</hi> he deſigned to regulate the Army for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly commanded by <hi>Popilius,</hi> and for more Advantage decamp'd to a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vater place. That day the <hi>Numantines,</hi> after an old Cuſtom proffer'd their Daughters in publick to be Married; it happened, that two young Men
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:99029:55"/>Courted the ſame pretty Woman, her Father told the Rivals, <hi>He only ſhould marry her, who ſlew an Enemy, and brought him his Right Hand.</hi> Both of them going out to execute this Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and obſerving the <hi>Romans</hi> to draw off in as much haſte as if they fled, acquainted their own party with it, who preſently ſallying out with Four thouſand, ſlew Twenty thouſand of the <hi>Romans. Mancinus,</hi> by the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of his Queſtor, <hi>Tiberius Gracchus</hi> made a League with the Enemy, upon their own Terms, which being diſliked by the Senate, <hi>Mancinus</hi> was deliver'd up to the <hi>Numantines,</hi> but not received for ſatisfaction by them. This unfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunate General was degraded, and durſt not return to the Camp, yet af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward by good Omens of the Sooth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayers he was advanced to the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of Pretor.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="biography">
                  <pb n="87" facs="tcp:99029:55"/>
                  <head>L. MUMMIUS ACHAI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CUS.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>L. Mummius</hi> was ſirnamed <hi>Achaicus,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">U.C. <hi>606.</hi>
                     </note> from Conquering <hi>Achaia:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Before Ch. <hi>144.</hi>
                     </note> in his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulſhip he was ordered to proſecute the War againſt the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> and and had the Honor of a Victory, which, in merit, was rather due to his Predeceſſor. For after <hi>Metellus Mace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donicus</hi> had routed the Enemy at <hi>Hera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clea,</hi> a City of <hi>Elis</hi> in the <hi>Peloponneſe,</hi> and killed their General <hi>Critolaus,</hi> he haſtened with his Serjeants, and a few Horſe to <hi>Metellus</hi>'s Camp to ſhare the Good Fortnne of the Battel, and with more eaſe defeated the Enemy at <hi>Leu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>topetra</hi> in the <hi>Iſthmus</hi> of <hi>Corinth. Diae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> their Commander fled, in deſpair ſet his Houſe on Fire, killed his Wife, threw her into the Flames, and then poiſoned himſelf. <hi>Mummius</hi> plun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered <hi>Corinth,</hi> and adorned <hi>Italy</hi> with their Pictures and Statues, yet ſo mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dente, as to carry none to his own Horſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="biography">
                  <pb n="88" facs="tcp:99029:56"/>
                  <head>Q. CAECILIUS METEL<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LUS MACEDONICUS.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">U.C. <hi>606.</hi>
                     </note>
                     <hi>Quinctus Caecilius Metelluss</hi> obtain'd the Title of <hi>Macedonicus,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Before Ch. <hi>144.</hi>
                     </note> from ſubduing <hi>Macedonia.</hi> In his Praetorſhip he over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came the Impoſtor <hi>Andriſcus,</hi> who aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed the Name of King <hi>Philip,</hi> he routed the <hi>Achaians</hi> twice, but <hi>Mum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mius</hi> intercepted the Glory of the Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph. The People, to ſhew their Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred towards him for his Severity, with much Difficulty choſe him Conſul, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter he had miſs'd it at two Elections. He vanquiſhed the <hi>Arbachi</hi> in <hi>Spai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>,</hi> and with great Courage before the Town <hi>Contrebia,</hi> made thoſe Cohorts which gave way to rally and regain their Poſt; he was ſo cloſe and ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prizing in his Counſels, that he an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered one of his Friends, inquiring into his Reſolutions, <hi>He would bur his Coat, if he thought it knew his nind.</hi> He was the happy Father of four va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liant Sons, who carried him to his
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:99029:56"/>Grave, three of whom he ſaw hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with a Conſulate, and the other with a Triumph.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="biography">
                  <head>Q. CAECILIUS METEL<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LUS NUMIDICUS.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">U.C. <hi>643.</hi>
                     </note>
                     <hi>Q. Caecilius Metellus</hi> in his Conſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip triumphed over <hi>Jugurtha,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Before Ch. <hi>107.</hi>
                     </note> King of <hi>Numidia,</hi> and from thence called <hi>Nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>midicus;</hi> when he was Cenſor he ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naliz'd his Integrity by refuſing to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roll in the publick Regiſter the Name of <hi>Quinctius,</hi> who ſcandalouſly pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to be the Son of <hi>Tiberius Grac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chus,</hi> and choſe rather to be baniſh'd than agree to the Law which <hi>Apuleius</hi> by violence impoſed upon them. He lived in Exile at <hi>Smyrna,</hi> and at laſt was recalled by <hi>Calidius,</hi> Tribune of the People. He always diſcovered a Conſtancy in his Temper, as appear'd in the Theatre, by not reading the Letter which was brought him till the Show was over, and by not making a Funeral Oration in Commendation of
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:99029:57"/>
                     <hi>Lucullus,</hi> his Siſter <hi>Metella's</hi> Husband, who had been the only perſon wrought upon to recant his Vote againſt the <hi>Agrarian</hi> and <hi>Frumentarian</hi> Laws.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="biography">
                  <head>Q. METELLUS PIUS.</head>
                  <p>He was the Son of <hi>Metellus Numidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">U.C. <hi>660.</hi>
                     </note> and honor'd with the <hi>Cognomen</hi> of <hi>Pius</hi> for his Filial Duty,<note place="margin">Before Ch. <hi>90.</hi>
                     </note> and continual Interceſſion with Tears to have his Father recall'd from Baniſtment. He ſhewed his Valour in the Social War, in which he commanded as Praetor, and kill'd <hi>Q. Popedius,</hi> General of the <hi>Marſi.</hi> He was ſent Conſul into <hi>Spain,</hi> where he defeated the <hi>Herculeii,</hi> Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenants to <hi>Sertorius,</hi> and forc'd him out of that Country. In his Youth, when he was Candidate for the Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torſhip, and Pontificat, he was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred to his Competitors of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſular Dignity.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="Shirley" type="translator">
               <pb n="91" facs="tcp:99029:57"/>
               <head>The HONORABLE Mr. <hi>WASHINGTON SHIRLEY.</hi> From the Year 619, to 670 <hi>U. C.</hi>
               </head>
               <div type="biography">
                  <head>TIBERIUS GRACCH<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Tiberius Gracchus,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">U.C. <hi>619.</hi>
                     </note> Grandſon to <hi>Scipio Africanus,</hi> by his Daughter <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nelia,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Before Ch. <hi>131.</hi>
                     </note> was Quaeſtor under <hi>Mancinus</hi> in <hi>Spain,</hi> and conſented to the making of that diſhonorable League with the <hi>Numantini:</hi> but by his plauſible Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence eſcaped being delivered up to them. When he was Tribune of the People he made two Laws, one that no perſon whatſoever ſhould poſſeſs above Five hundred Acres of Land, the other that the Eſtate which <hi>Attalus</hi> King of <hi>Pergamus</hi> bequeathed to the Commonwealth, ſhould be divided
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:99029:58"/>among the People. His Colleague <hi>Octavius</hi> zealouſly oppoſed the former; and was therefore turned out of his Office contrary to all Precedents. At the following Election, in hopes of continuing another year in his Office, he came into the Aſſembly, tho the Predictions of Augurs were againſt him, and went directly towards the Capitol, putting his Hand to his Head, by which Geſture he deſired the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection of the People: but the Nobili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty thought that he then demanded the Crown: and <hi>Mucius</hi> the Conſul being tardy in purſuing him, <hi>Scipio Naſica</hi> commanded all thoſe that wiſhed well to the Safety of; the Commonwealth to follow him, and ſeizing upon <hi>Grac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chus</hi> in the Capitol ſlew him: <hi>Lucretius</hi> the Aedile took up his Body, and threw it into, the River <hi>Tiber,</hi> from whence he was nicknamed <hi>Veſpillo. Naſica,</hi> that he might be out of the way; and ſecured from popular Odi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um, went under Colour of an Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſdor into <hi>Aſia.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="biography">
                  <pb n="93" facs="tcp:99029:58"/>
                  <head>CAIUS GRACCHUS.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">U.C. <hi>629.</hi>
                     </note>
                     <hi>Caius Gracchus</hi> was made Quaeſtor of that unhealthſul Iſland of <hi>Sardinia,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Before Ch. <hi>131.</hi>
                     </note> and at the expiration of his Year left the place, contrary to Law, before any one came to ſucceed him. He bore the Blame of the Revolt of <hi>Aſculum</hi> and <hi>Fregellae.</hi> When he was Tribune of the People he ſet up the Laws a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the Diviſion of Lands, and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtribution of Corn among the People, and was for ſending Colonies to. <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pua</hi> and <hi>Tarentum.</hi> He made <hi>Fulvius Flaccus</hi> and <hi>C. Craſlus</hi> Joint-Commiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners with himſelf for the Diviſion of the Lands. <hi>Minucius Rufus,</hi> Tribune of the People, oppoſing his Actions as ſeditious, he went with his party for ſecurity into the Capitol, yet after he ſaw <hi>Atilius,</hi> one of <hi>Opimius,</hi> the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſul's Serjeants, killed by the Crowd, he came down into the <hi>Forum,</hi> and imprudently broke up the Aſſembly held there by <hi>Minucius Rufus,</hi> Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bune of the People; for which Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demeanour
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:99029:59"/>he was ſummoned to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear before the Senate, but in defiance to them, he armed all his Servants<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and poſſeſſed himſelf of Mount <hi>Aven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine,</hi> where he was routed by <hi>Opimius,</hi> and leaping from the Temple of <hi>Diana</hi> for<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> fear of being taken Priſoner, ſprained his Ancle: his Friend <hi>Pompo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius</hi> ſtopping thoſe that purſued him at the Gate called <hi>Trigemina,</hi> and <hi>Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius Laetorius</hi> detaining others at the Wooden Bridge, he made his Eſcape into the Goddeſs <hi>Furina</hi>'s Wood, when he was killed, either by <hi>Euphorus</hi> his Servant, or by himſelf. 'Tis report<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that his Head was carried by <hi>Septimuleius</hi> his Friend, to <hi>Opimius</hi> the Conſul, and ſold for its Weight in Gold. And that through Covetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs he filled it with Lead, to make it the heavier.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="biography">
                  <head>M. LUCIUS DRUSUS.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">U.C. <hi>640.</hi>
                     </note>
                     <hi>Marcus Lucius Druſus</hi> deſcended of a Noble Family,<note place="margin">Before Ch. <hi>110.</hi>
                     </note> was very eloquent, but ambitious and proud. In his Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dileſhip he gratified the People with a
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:99029:59"/>moſt magnificent Shew, at which time <hi>Remmius</hi> his Colleague adviſing ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing for the Good of the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, he anſwered him arrogantly, <hi>What have you to do with my Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth?</hi> When he was Quaeſtor in <hi>Aſia.</hi> he would not appear in publick with the Badges of Honor, that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing might be taken notice of, as greater than himſelf. When he was Tribune of the People he promiſed the <hi>Latins</hi> to make them free of the City, he divided Lands amongſt the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon People, and by way of Exchange. granted the <hi>Roman</hi> Gentlemen the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vilege of ſitting in the Senate Houſe, and the Senators the manage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Court of Judicature. He was ſo extravagantly liberal, that he declared, he had left no Magiſtrate for the future any thing to give away, but the Heavens and the Dirt of the Earth. Hence wanting Money, he did many things beneath his Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour. For Money he delivered up to King <hi>Bocchus, Magulſa,</hi> a Prince of <hi>Mauritania,</hi> who had left his Country
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:99029:60"/>for fear of the King's diſpleaſure, and was devour'd aftertwards by an Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phant: and alſo he concealed in his Houſe <hi>Adherbal,</hi> Son to the King of <hi>Numidia,</hi> reſiding at <hi>Rome,</hi> as an Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtage in hopes of receiving a large Ranſom from his Father. He was ſo haughty, that he threatened to throw his Adverſary <hi>Servilius Caepio,</hi> headlong from the <hi>Tarpeian</hi> Rock, for oppoſing him. And when <hi>Philip</hi> the Conſul would not conſent to his Laws about the Diviſion of Lands, he twiſted his Neck before the People ſo violently, that a great quantity of Blood guſhed out at his Noſtrils, which he, to up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braid him for his Luxury, ſaid, <hi>Was not Blood, but the Gravy of Thruſhes.</hi> Ar laſt he was hated, as much as he had been formerly beloved; for tho ſome People were glad at their receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Lands, yet others were vexed at their being turned out. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of the Gentlemen were pleaſed with the Liberty of coming into the Senate, but they whoſe Names were omitted by the Cenſor, took it ill.</p>
                  <pb n="97" facs="tcp:99029:60"/>
                  <p>The Senators were ſatisfied with the privilege of having power in the Courts of Judicature, but were diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſed that the Gentlemen ſhould be ranked with them. Whereupon <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vius</hi> in great perplexity how to put off the Demands of the <hi>Latins</hi> who preſſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to be made free of the City ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his promiſe, on a ſudden fell down in the Street, either of an Epilepſie, or having drunk on purpoſe ſome Goats Blood He Was carried home half dead, publick Prayers were made for him over all <hi>Italy,</hi> and when the <hi>Latins</hi> deſigned to kill the Conſul at the great Feſtival on Mount <hi>Alban,</hi> he gave <hi>Philip</hi> notice to take care of himſelf; for this he was afterwards accuſed in the Senate, and aſſaſſin'd in the Street one time as he was a going home, by <hi>Philip</hi> and <hi>Caepio,</hi> as 'twas generally ſuſpected.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="biography">
                  <pb n="98" facs="tcp:99029:61"/>
                  <head>C. MARIUS <hi>the Father.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Caius Marius</hi> was ſeven times Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful,<note place="margin">U.C. <hi>650.</hi>
                     </note> born of mean Parentage at <hi>Arpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Before Ch. <hi>100.</hi>
                     </note> but by degrees advanced to the higheſt Places of Honor. Whilſt he was Lieutenant under <hi>Metellus</hi> in <hi>Nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>midia</hi> he got the Conſulſhip, by ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſing him, and taking <hi>Jugurtha</hi> pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner, led him in Triumph before his Chariot. He was choſe Conſul for the year enſuing, <hi>nemine contradicente,</hi> and triumph'd for his Victory over the <hi>Teutones</hi> in <hi>Gaul</hi> at <hi>Aquae Sextiae,</hi> and the <hi>Cimbri</hi> in <hi>Italy</hi> in the <hi>Claudian</hi> Fields. In his ſixth Conſulate which he enjoyed ſix years ſucceſſively, by a Decree of the Senate he put to Death <hi>Apuleius Saturninus,</hi> Tribune of the People, and <hi>Glaucias</hi> the Paetor, for raiſing a Sedition. When he would have ſupplanted <hi>Sulla</hi> by <hi>Sulpicius</hi>'s Law, and been General in his ſtead in the War againſt <hi>Mithridates,</hi> he was driven out of <hi>Rome</hi> by his power, and forced to hide himſelf in a Marſh at
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:99029:61"/>
                     <hi>Minturnae.</hi> Upon his Diſcovery he was caſt into priſon, and by his Majeſtick Look frightened the <hi>Gaul</hi> that was ſent to execute him. Whence eſcaping in a ſmall Veſſel, he paſſed into <hi>Africk,</hi> and lived there a long time in Baniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. But at laſt recalled by <hi>Cinna</hi> the Conſul, he broke open all Work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſes, and muſtered up an Army of Slaves, and glutting his Revenge by the Slaughter of his Enemies, in his ſeventh Conſulſhip, ſome ſay, the kill<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed himſelf.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="biography">
                  <head>C. MARIUS <hi>the Son.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">U.C. <hi>670.</hi>
                     </note>
                     <hi>Caius Marius</hi> the Younger invaded the Conſulſhip at Five and twenty years of Age,<note place="margin">Before Ch. <hi>80.</hi>
                     </note> which over early Honor, his Mother with Tears lamented; for he was as cruel as his Father, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet the Senate-Houſe, murther'd his Enemies, and threw their Bodies into the River <hi>Tiber.</hi> In his Preparations for the War againſt <hi>Sulla,</hi> whilſt he lay down in the open air to refreſh himſelf, tired out with watching and labor at
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:99029:62"/>
                     <hi>Sacriportus,</hi> his Forces were routed as he ſlept, and he came up to them on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly time enough to run away amongſt them. He fled from thence to <hi>Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſte,</hi> where <hi>Lucretius Offella</hi> block'd him up, and trying to make his eſcape through ſome ſubterraneous Paſſages, but finding them all ſecured he deſired <hi>Pentius Geleſinus</hi> to kill him.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="biography">
                  <head>LUCIUS CORNELIUS CINNA.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">U.C. <hi>665.</hi>
                     </note>
                     <hi>Lucius Cornelius Cinna</hi> was a very wicked Man,<note place="margin">Before Ch. <hi>85.</hi>
                     </note> and by his unparallel'd Cruelty almoſt ruin'd the Common-wealth. In his firſt Conſulſhip he would have made a Law for recalling the Exiles, but was oppos'd by his Colleague <hi>Octavius,</hi> and turned out of his Office. Upon which he left the City, and making all the Slaves free, by their aſſiſtance vanquiſhed his Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, killed <hi>Octavius,</hi> and got poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Mount <hi>Janiculus.</hi> He made himſelf Conſul a ſecond, third and
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:99029:62"/>fourth time; and then as he was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring for a War againſt <hi>Sulla,</hi> he was ſtoned to death by his Army at <hi>Ancona,</hi> for his inſufferable Cruelty.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="biography">
                  <head>C. FLAVIUS FIMBRIA.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Caius Flavius Fimbria,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">U.C. <hi>665.</hi>
                     </note> one of the cruelleſt of <hi>Cinna</hi>'s Officers,<note place="margin">Before Ch. <hi>85.</hi>
                     </note> went Lieutenant under <hi>Valerius Flaccus</hi> the Conſul into <hi>Aſia,</hi> but was diſmiſſed upon ſome private Grudge, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge himſelf by his corrupt Practices he prevailed with the Army to revolt, and kill'd their General. Then ſeiſing on the <hi>Inſignia</hi> that belonged to the Conſul, he took the Government upon himſelf, and beat <hi>Mithridates</hi> out of <hi>Pergamus,</hi> giving Orders that <hi>Ilium</hi> ſhould be burnt becauſe they did not open their Gates ſoon enough to him, and put all the Officers in the Garri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to the Sword, but <hi>Minerva</hi>'s Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple received not the leaſt Damage by the Flames, preſerved in every ones Opinion by the Power of the God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſs.
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:99029:63"/>Soon after he was block'd up by <hi>Sulla</hi> at <hi>Pergamus,</hi> and ſeeing his Army deſert him, ſlew himſelf.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="biography">
                  <head>VIRIATHUS LUSITANUS.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Viriathus</hi> a <hi>Luſitanian,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">U.C. <hi>619.</hi>
                     </note> by reaſon of his great Poverty was at firſt a Day-Labourer,<note place="margin">Before Ch. <hi>131.</hi>
                     </note> then for his Activity a Huntſman, for his Boldneſs a Robber, and at laſt a great Commander. He waged War againſt the <hi>Romans,</hi> and beat firſt their General <hi>Claudius Unima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus,</hi> and afterwards <hi>Caius Nigidius.</hi> He was willing to make peace with the <hi>Romans</hi> while his Arms were ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsful; but after he was routed by them, and had yielded up all things elſe upon the ſeizure of their Arms he renewed the War. And <hi>Caepio</hi> find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that he could overcome him no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther way, hired two of his Guards to kill him, as he lay drunk upon the Ground, but the Senate did not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove of this Victory, ſince it was bought by Treachery.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="Cavendish" type="translator">
               <pb n="103" facs="tcp:99029:63"/>
               <head>The Honorable Mr. JAMES CAVENDISH. From the Year 642, to 689, <hi>U. C.</hi>
               </head>
               <div type="biography">
                  <head>MARCUS AEMILIUS SCAURUS.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>MArcus Aemilius Scaurus,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">U.C. <hi>642.</hi>
                     </note> was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcended of a Noble Family,<note place="margin">Before Ch. <hi>108.</hi>
                     </note> yet poor; for his Father, tho a Senator's Son, was a Collier by Trade. He at firſt doubted with himſelf whether he ſhould aim at great Employments in the Commonwealth, or get an Eſtate by turning Banker, but being very e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loquent he ſoon grew famous. For his good Service in <hi>Spain</hi> he was made a Cornet of Horſe, and ſerved under <hi>Oreſtes</hi> the Conſul in <hi>Sardinia.</hi> When
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:99029:64"/>he was Aedile he minded doing of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice more than courting the People with public Shews: he was Lieute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant under <hi>Calpurnius</hi> in the <hi>African</hi> War againſt <hi>Jugurtha,</hi> whom he much oppoſed in the beginning, but at laſt was corrupted by him: when he was Conſul he made a Law about regula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Expences, and the Freed Men giving their Votes. He was ſo haughty, becauſe that <hi>Publius Decius</hi> the Praetor did not riſe up and ſalute him as he paſſed by, he commanded him to ſtand up, tore his Gown, and broke his Chair of State in pieces, and ordered that none ſhould have any Cauſes tryed before him. In his Conſulſhip he conquered the <hi>Gantiſci</hi> and <hi>Ligures,</hi> and triumphed over them. When he was Cenſor he paved the <hi>Aemilian</hi> Way, and made the <hi>Mulvian</hi> Bridge, he was a Man of ſuch Credit and Intereſt, that upon his private Advice, <hi>Opimius</hi> took up Arms againſt <hi>Gracchus</hi> and <hi>Marius,</hi> againſt <hi>Glaucias</hi> and <hi>Saturninus.</hi> He would never look upon his Son for deſerting his Poſt,
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:99029:64"/>which Diſgrace made him kill himſelf. Growing old he was accuſed by <hi>Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius,</hi> Tribune of the People, for ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring up the <hi>Latins</hi> and the Allies to Rebellion. Whereupon he ſaid to the People; Varius <hi>of</hi> Sucro <hi>ſays, That</hi> Aemilius Scaurus <hi>ſtirred up the Allies to take up Arms; but</hi> Scaurus <hi>denies it: Whether of the two think you more worthy of Credit?</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="biography">
                  <head>LUCIUS APULEIUS SATURNINUS.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Lucius Apuleius Saturninus,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">U.C. <hi>658.</hi>
                     </note> Tribune of the People, was a ſeditious Man,<note place="margin">Before Ch. <hi>92.</hi>
                     </note> and to ingratiate himſelf with the Soldiers of <hi>Marius</hi>'s party, made a Law, That an Hundred Acres of Land in <hi>Africa</hi> ſhould be divided amongſt the old Soldiers, and made his Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>league <hi>Baebius,</hi> that oppoſed this Law, fly for it, ſtirring up the People to ſtone him. To make himſel more popular, he broke in pieces <hi>Glaucias</hi> the Praetor's Chair, becauſe he, by keeping a Court on the ſame day, that
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:99029:65"/>he held an Aſſembly about dividing the Land, had drawn away a great part of the People. He ſuborned a Freeman to pretend he was the Son of <hi>Tiberius Gracchus,</hi> and <hi>Sempronia, Gracchus</hi>'s Siſter was produced to juſtifie it, but ſhe would not be prevailed upon, either by Entreaty or Threats to bring ſuch a ſcandal upon her Family. <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turninus,</hi> after <hi>Aulus Nonius,</hi> his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petitor was ſlain, was again choſe Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bune of the People, and planted new Colonies in <hi>Sicily, Macedonia</hi> and <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaia,</hi> and brought Land with the Gold which <hi>Caepio</hi> had ſacrilegiouſly taken from <hi>Toloſa</hi> in <hi>Gaul.</hi> He baniſhed all them that would not conſent to his Laws. And he told many Noble Men that oppoſed them whilſt it acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentally thundered, that if they would not be quiet and ſubmit, it ſhould pour down a ſtorm of Hail. However <hi>Metellus Numidicus</hi> choſe ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to be baniſh'd than ſwear to them. When <hi>Saturninus</hi> was a third time Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bune of the People, that he might make his Companion <hi>Glaucias</hi> the Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor-Conſul,
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:99029:65"/>he cauſe <hi>Memmius,</hi> who oppoſed him, to be killed in the <hi>Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus Martius. Marius</hi> taking Arms by virtue of an Order of the Senate, which required the Conſuls to take care of the Common-wealth, purſued <hi>Saturninus</hi> and <hi>Glaucias</hi> into the Capi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tol, and there beſieged them, and cut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the Water-Pipes, forced them to ſurrender. But he hid not keep his Word with them; for the ordered <hi>Glau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cias</hi> to be ſtrangled, and <hi>Apuleius</hi> fly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing into the Capitol, was <hi>Apuleius</hi> fly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing into the Capitol, was killed by the Stones and Tiles thrown at him. <hi>Rabirius,</hi> one of the Senators carried his Head into ſeveral Houſes, to make ſport with at their Entertainments.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="biography">
                  <head>LUCIUS LICINIUS LUCULLUS.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">U.C. <hi>680.</hi>
                     </note>
                     <hi>Lucius Licinius Lucullus</hi> was of a Noble Family,<note place="margin">Before Ch. <hi>70.</hi>
                     </note> eloquent and rich, and preſented a very magnificent Shew to the People in his Quaeſtorſhip. He reconciled <hi>Ptolemy,</hi> King of <hi>Alexandria</hi> to
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:99029:66"/>
                     <hi>Sulla</hi> the Conſul, and by <hi>Murena</hi> brought over to him <hi>Mithridate</hi>'s Fleet, he adminiſtred Juſtice very impar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tially during his Praetorſhip in <hi>Africa.</hi> Being ſent Conſul againſt <hi>Mithridates,</hi> he relieved his Colleague <hi>Cotta,</hi> that was block'd up at <hi>Chalcedon,</hi> a City of <hi>Bithynia.</hi> He raiſed the Siege of <hi>Cyzi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus,</hi> ſtarved and cut off <hi>Mithridates</hi>'s Forces, and drove him out of his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom <hi>Pontus,</hi> and beat him a ſecond time with great ſucceſs, when <hi>Tigranus</hi> King of <hi>Armenia</hi> had joined him with his auxiliary Forces. He was extrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vagant in his Cloaths, and delighted much in Statues and Pictures: after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards when from a Diſorder in his Head he began to dote, he was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to the Guardianſhip of his Brother <hi>Marcus Lucullus.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="biography">
                  <head>LUCIUS CORNELIUS SULLA.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>L. Cornelius Sulla</hi> was ſirnamed <hi>Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lix,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">U.C. <hi>669.</hi>
                     </note> from his good Fortune.<note place="margin">Before Ch. <hi>81.</hi>
                     </note> When
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:99029:66"/>he was a little Child, and carried a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout in his Nurſe's Arms, a Woman met him, and ſaid, <hi>God bleſs thee, Child, thou wilt prove fortunate to thy ſelf, and thy Country.</hi> But who that Woman was, no Body could tell, for ſhe was never heard of afterwards. When he was Quaeſtor under <hi>Marius, Bocchus</hi> King of <hi>Mauritania</hi> delivered up <hi>Jugurtha</hi> to him. In the <hi>Cimbrian</hi> and <hi>Teutonick</hi> Wars he was choſen Lieute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant General to <hi>Marius,</hi> and did good ſervice. He was firſt Praetor at <hi>Rome,</hi> and then ſent Praetor into <hi>Cilicia.</hi> In the Social War againſt the <hi>Italian</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federates, he overcame the <hi>Samnites</hi> and the <hi>Irpini.</hi> He oppoſed <hi>Marius</hi>'s taking down, out of Envy, the Pictures of <hi>Bocchus</hi>'s delivering up <hi>Jugurtha</hi> to him: being Conſul in <hi>Aſia,</hi> he routed <hi>Mithridates</hi> at <hi>Orchomenum</hi> and <hi>Chaero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naea,</hi> and overcame his General <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chelaus</hi> at <hi>Athens,</hi> and retook the <hi>Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raean</hi> Haven. He overcame the <hi>Dar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dani,</hi> and the <hi>Eneti,</hi> in his March: and after his Province was taken from him by the <hi>Sulpician</hi> Law, and given
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:99029:67"/>to <hi>Marius,</hi> returning upon this Affront into <hi>Italy,</hi> and corrupting his Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries Army, he made <hi>Carbo</hi> fly for it; he overcame <hi>Marius</hi> the younger at <hi>Sacriportus,</hi> and <hi>Teleſinus</hi> at the Gate of <hi>Rome,</hi> called <hi>Collina.</hi> Upon theſe De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feats, and the Death of <hi>Marius</hi> at <hi>Praeneſte,</hi> by a publick Edict he ſir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>named himſelf <hi>Felix,</hi> or <hi>The Fortunate:</hi> he was the firſt that propoſed the Tables of Proſcription, and cut off Nine thouſand that ſurrendered them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in the <hi>Campus Martius:</hi> he aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented the number of Prieſts, and leſſened the Power of the Tribunes. And after he had ſettled the Affairs of the Commonwealth, reſigned his Dictatorſhip, and finding upon this, that he grew contemptible, he went to <hi>Puteoli,</hi> and there died of the lowſie Diſeaſe called <hi>Phtiriaſis.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="biography">
                  <head>MITHRIDATES, <hi>King of</hi> Pontus.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Mithridates,</hi> King of <hi>Pontus,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">U.C. <hi>664.</hi>
                     </note> deſcend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from one of the ſeven <hi>Perſian</hi> He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roes,<note place="margin">Before Ch. <hi>86.</hi>
                     </note>
                     <pb n="111" facs="tcp:99029:67"/>that killed the Impoſtor ſet up by the <hi>Magi,</hi> could ſpeak two and twenty Languages, and was ſo ſtrong, that he could drive a Chariot and Six Horſes. Whilſt the <hi>Romans</hi> were quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>relling with the Allies, he beat <hi>Nicome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des</hi> out of <hi>Bithynia, Ariobarzanes</hi> out of <hi>Cappadocia,</hi> and ſent Orders all over <hi>Aſia,</hi> to have every <hi>Roman</hi> maſſacred that ſhould be found there on a certain day, which was done accordingly. He ſeized on <hi>Greece,</hi> and all the Iſlands that belonged to the <hi>Romans,</hi> except <hi>Rhodes.</hi> But <hi>Sulla</hi> beat him in a pitch'd Battel, took his Fleet by the Treachery of <hi>Archelaus,</hi> and totally routed him at the City <hi>Orchomenus,</hi> and might have cut off his whole Army, had he not been in haſte to go againſt <hi>Marius,</hi> and ſo was glad to make peace upon any Terms. Afterwards upon his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king Head againſt the <hi>Romans</hi> at <hi>Cabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra,</hi> he was overcome by <hi>Lucullus,</hi> and and at another time by <hi>Pompey,</hi> who gave him Battel by Night. Thence he fled into his own Kingdom, and upon the Rebellion of his Subjects, headed
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:99029:68"/>by his Son <hi>Pharnaces,</hi> finding the Tower beſet, the place of his Retreat, he took a Doſe of Poiſon, which ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving little effect, becauſe he had for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly taken ſo many Antidotes, when <hi>Sithocus</hi> the <hi>Gaul</hi> was ſent to execute him, and was ſtartled at his Majeſtick Look, he bade him do his Office, and aſſiſted his trembling Hand in the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="biography">
                  <head>CNAEUS POMPEIUS MAGNUS.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">U.C. <hi>689.</hi>
                     </note>
                     <hi>Cnaeus Pompeius the Great</hi> ſided with <hi>Sulla</hi> in the Civil War,<note place="margin">Before Ch. <hi>61.</hi>
                     </note> and behaved himſelf ſo well, that he was mightily beloved by him. He retook <hi>Sicily</hi> from the proſcribed perſons that fled thither, without any oppoſition, turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Hiarbas</hi> out of <hi>Numidia,</hi> and reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red <hi>Maſſiniſſa,</hi> he rode in Triumph into the City when he was but Six and twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty years old, and tho he was but a private Man, forced <hi>Lepidus</hi> to leave <hi>Italy,</hi> for endeavouring to reſcind <hi>Sulla</hi>'s Laws of Proſcription: when he was
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:99029:68"/>ſent Praetor into <hi>Spain,</hi> inſtead of the Conſuls, he conquered <hi>Sertorius,</hi> and not long after cleared the Sea of Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates within Forty Days, he forced <hi>Tigranes</hi> to ſurrender, and <hi>Mithridates</hi> to poiſon himſelf. Then with great Fortune, and no leſs Expedition, he went firſt into the North againſt the <hi>Albani,</hi> the <hi>Colchi,</hi> the <hi>Heniochi, Caſpii, Iberi,</hi> and in the Eaſt ſtruck Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror into the <hi>Parthians, Arabians</hi> and <hi>Jews.</hi> He was the firſt <hi>Roman</hi> that went as far as the <hi>Hyrcanian</hi> or <hi>Caſpian,</hi> the <hi>Red</hi> or <hi>Arabian</hi> Sea. Upon the Diviſion of the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire, <hi>Craſſus</hi> had the Government of <hi>Syria, Caeſar</hi> of <hi>Gaul,</hi> and <hi>Pompey</hi> of <hi>Rome.</hi> After the Death of <hi>Craſſus</hi> he commanded <hi>Caeſar</hi> to disband his Army, but he refuſed to do it, and coming againſt <hi>Pompey,</hi> drove him out of the City, and beat him in <hi>Pharſalia,</hi> from whence he fled to <hi>Ptolemy,</hi> King of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> and was by his command killed by <hi>Achillas</hi> and <hi>Pothinus,</hi> two of his Life-Guard. <hi>Septimius,</hi> Captain of the Guard, ſtab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed him in the ſight of his Wife and
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:99029:69"/>Children, and cut off his Head, which until that time had been looked upon as Sacred, his Body was thrown into the River <hi>Nile,</hi> but taken up by <hi>Servius Codrus,</hi> and buried with this Inſcription upon his Tomb. <hi>Here lies</hi> Pompey <hi>the Great.</hi> His Head was wrapt up in a Cloth by <hi>Achillas,</hi> and preſented with his Ring to <hi>Caeſar,</hi> who could not forbear Tears at the ſight of it, and gave order to have it burnt with many rich Perfumes.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="Lloyd" type="translator">
               <pb n="115" facs="tcp:99029:69"/>
               <head>Mr. <hi>JAMES LLOYD.</hi> From the Year 670, to 722 <hi>U. C.</hi>
               </head>
               <div type="biography">
                  <head>JULIUS CAESAR.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>CAius Julius Caeſar,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">U.C. <hi>697.</hi>
                     </note> in honor of his great Exploits, ſirnamed <hi>Divus,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Before Ch. <hi>53.</hi>
                     </note> went Voluntier into <hi>Aſia,</hi> in the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue of <hi>Thermus</hi> the Praetor, where, by converſing too often with <hi>Nicome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des,</hi> King of <hi>Bithynia,</hi> he was ſuſpected of Incontinency. After this he ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied himſelf to the Bar, and proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted <hi>Dolobella</hi> for Bribery, and had him condemned. In his Voyage to <hi>Rhodes,</hi> where he deſign'd to ſtudy under <hi>Apollonius Molo,</hi> he was taken by Pyrats, and paid a great Ranſom, yet in revenge he ſoon after took the ſame Pirats, and crucified them. When he was choſe Praetor he ſubdued <hi>Luſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tania,</hi>
                     <pb n="116" facs="tcp:99029:70"/>and all <hi>Gaul</hi> on the other ſide of the <hi>Alpes,</hi> and twice croſſing the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cean with his Fleet, conquered <hi>Britain.</hi> Upon <hi>Pompey</hi>'s denying him a public Triumph, he drove him out of <hi>Rome</hi> by Force of Arms, and beat him at <hi>Pharſalia</hi> in <hi>Theſſaly;</hi> yet when his Head was brought to him in <hi>Aegypt</hi> by <hi>Achillas,</hi> he wept, and gave order to have it honourably buried: and took the oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of King <hi>Ptolemy</hi>'s Guards ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting upon him, to expiate the Murder of <hi>Pompey</hi> upon them and their King. The Terror of his very Name put <hi>Pharnaces,</hi> the Son of <hi>Mithridates,</hi> to flight. He overcame <hi>Juba</hi> and <hi>Scipio</hi> in <hi>Africa,</hi> the two <hi>Pompeys</hi> in a Battel at <hi>Munda</hi> in <hi>Spain;</hi> and then forgiving his Enemies, laid down his Arms with all private Grudges, for he command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that only <hi>Lentulus, Afranius,</hi> and <hi>Fauſtus</hi> the Son of <hi>Sylla</hi> ſhould be put to Death. He was made perpetual Dictator by the Senate, and aſſaſſin'd in the Senate Houſe by ſome Conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rators headed by <hi>Brutus</hi> and <hi>Caſſius,</hi> with Three and twenty Wounds. When
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:99029:70"/>his Body was laid before the Pulpit, where <hi>Marc Anthony</hi> made his Funeral Oration, ſome ſay, the Sun was E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clipſed.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="biography">
                  <head>OCTAVIANUS CAESAR.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">U.C. <hi>721.</hi>
                     </note>
                     <hi>Caeſar Octavianus</hi> was adopted from the <hi>Octavian</hi> into the <hi>Julian</hi> Family:<note place="margin">Before Ch. <hi>29.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Julius Caeſar</hi> made him his Heir, and to revenge his Murther, he conquered <hi>Brutus</hi> and <hi>Caſſius</hi> in <hi>Macedonia,</hi> who were principally concerned in that Conſpiracy; and at the Streights of <hi>Sicily</hi> overcame <hi>Sextus Pompeius,</hi> the Son of <hi>Cneus Pompeius,</hi> when he endeavoured to recover his Father's Eſtate. Upon the Coaſt of <hi>Actium,</hi> near the Gulf of <hi>Ambracia,</hi> he totally routed the Fleet commanded by <hi>Marc Antony,</hi> who was deeply in love with <hi>Cleopatra,</hi> and governed <hi>Syria</hi> as Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſul. The reſt of the World was ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued by his Lieutenants. The <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thians,</hi> in honor to him, of their own accord, ſent him the Standards which they had formerly taken from <hi>Craſſus.</hi>
                     <pb n="118" facs="tcp:99029:71"/>The <hi>Indians, Scythians, Sarmatians</hi> and <hi>Dacians,</hi> althô he had not conquered them, ſent him Preſents. He ſhut the Gates of Two-faced <hi>Janus</hi>'s Temple with his own Hand, never ſhut but twice before his time, once in <hi>Numa Pompilius</hi>'s Reign, and a ſecond time after the firſt <hi>Carthaginian</hi> War. The Senate made him perpetual Dictator, and ſtil'd him <hi>Divus Auguſtus</hi> for his noble Actions.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="biography">
                  <head>CATO PRAETORIUS.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Cato Praetorius,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">U.C. <hi>689.</hi>
                     </note> great Grandſon to <hi>Cato</hi> the Cenſor,<note place="margin">Before Ch. <hi>61.</hi>
                     </note> was ever ſo firm to his Principles, that in his youth whilſt he was brought up in his Uncle <hi>Dru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus</hi>'s Houſe, <hi>Quintus Popedius Silo,</hi> chief Magiſtrate of the <hi>Marſi</hi> could not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuade him either by Bribes or Threats to ſay, That he would ſide with the Allies. When he was Quaeſtor he was ſent into <hi>Cyprus</hi> to fetch the Money that King <hi>Ptolemy</hi>'s Eſtate was ſold for, and brought it ſafe to <hi>Rome</hi> with great Integrity. He was ſo upright and
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:99029:71"/>juſt, that contrary to others, he voted the Death of the <hi>Catilinarian</hi> Conſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors. In the Civil War between <hi>Caeſar</hi> and <hi>Pompey,</hi> he ſided with the latter, and after his Overthrow, march'd the Army through the Deſarts of <hi>Africa,</hi> where he delivered up his Command to <hi>Scipio</hi> that had been Conſul, as ſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior to him, who was but a Praetor. When his party was beaten, he went to <hi>Utica,</hi> where adviſing his Son to ſubmit to <hi>Caeſar</hi>'s Mercy, he kill'd him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, having firſt read over <hi>Plato</hi>'s Book of the Souls Immortality, and Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs after Death.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="biography">
                  <head>
                     <note place="margin">U C. <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap>.</hi>
                     </note>MARCUS TULLIUS CICERO.<note place="margin">Before Ch. <hi>61.</hi>
                     </note>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Marcus Tullius Cicero</hi> was born at <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinum,</hi> his Father was a <hi>Roman</hi> Knight, deſcended from King <hi>Titus Tatius.</hi> At Seven and twenty years of Age he ſhewed his Eloquence and Boldneſs of Speech in the Cauſe between <hi>Roſcius</hi> and <hi>Sulla</hi>'s Party, and immediately after to ſecure himſelf, went to <hi>Athens</hi>
                     <pb n="120" facs="tcp:99029:72"/>to follow his Studies, and was a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Auditor of <hi>Antiochus</hi> the Aca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demick Philoſopher, from thence to improve his Eloquence he went into <hi>Aſia,</hi> and ſo to <hi>Rhodes,</hi> where <hi>Molo</hi> the <hi>Graecian,</hi> who was the greateſt Maſter of Rhetorick in thoſe Days, was his Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, and is ſaid to have wept when he parted with him, becauſe he thought the <hi>Graecians,</hi> then reputed the moſt eloquent Men in the World, would be outdone by him. He was Quaeſtor in <hi>Sicily,</hi> and in his Aedileſhip condemn'd <hi>Caius Verres</hi> for Extortion in his Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment. He governed <hi>Cilicia</hi> under the Title of Praetor, and cleared it from the Robbers, who had long peſtered the Country. In his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulſhip he put to death all that were Confederates in <hi>Catilin</hi>'s Conſpiracy: afterwards he was baniſhed by the Malice of <hi>Publius Clodius,</hi> at the inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation of <hi>Caeſar</hi> and <hi>Pompey,</hi> whom he had laſh'd as ſeverely as he formerly did <hi>Sulla</hi>'s Party, upon ſuſpicion of their aiming to get the Government into their Hands; <hi>Piſo</hi> and <hi>Gabinius</hi>
                     <pb n="121" facs="tcp:99029:72"/>the Conſuls were prevailed upon by <hi>Clodius</hi> to join in this Affair, and had for this Service the Provinces of <hi>Mace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donia</hi> and <hi>Syria</hi> aſſigned them. Yet ſoon after <hi>Pompey</hi> himſelf aſſerting his Cauſe in the Senate, he was recalled, and in the Civil War ſided with him; upon whoſe Overthrow <hi>Caeſar</hi> freely pardoned him; after <hi>Caeſar</hi> was mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered, he joyned with <hi>Auguſtus:</hi> and declared <hi>Mark Antony</hi> an Enemy to the Common-wealth. When <hi>Caeſar, Lepidus</hi> and <hi>Antony</hi> had made themſelves <hi>Trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viri,</hi> there was no likelyhood of their Agreement till <hi>Tully</hi> was cut off by the Table of Proſcription, <hi>Antony</hi> ſent Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutioners to kill him; and as he lay aſleep at his Houſe at <hi>Formiae,</hi> he had warning of his approaching danger by a Crow, which pulled him by his Cloak: they killed him in his Litter, as he was making his Eſcape, and brought his Head to <hi>Antony.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="biography">
                  <pb n="122" facs="tcp:99029:73"/>
                  <head>MARCUS BRUTUS.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Marcus Brutus</hi> was in the Conduct of his Life like his Uncle <hi>Cato,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">U.C. <hi>710.</hi>
                     </note> he learned Philoſophy at <hi>Athens,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Before Ch. <hi>40.</hi>
                     </note> and Rhetorick at <hi>Rhodes.</hi> In his youth he was amo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous; <hi>Antony, Gallus</hi> and he were in love with <hi>Cytheris</hi> the Actreſs. He would not go Quaeſtor into <hi>Gaul,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing oppoſed by ſome good Men. He was in <hi>Cilicia</hi> with <hi>Appius Claudius:</hi> and when his Colleague was accuſed of Extortion by <hi>Dolabella,</hi> he himſelf had nothing laid to his Charge. In the Civil War between <hi>Caeſar</hi> and <hi>Pom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pey</hi> he was ſent for out of <hi>Cilicia</hi> by <hi>Cato,</hi> and ſided with <hi>Pompey,</hi> however <hi>Caeſar</hi> pardoned him, and ſent him Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſul into <hi>Gaul;</hi> yet notwithſtanding all <hi>Caeſar</hi>'s kindneſs to him, he was one of the Conſpirators that killed him in the Senate Houſe. Hence being ſent in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Macedonia,</hi> becauſe <hi>Caeſar</hi>'s old Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers were incenſed againſt him, he was overcome by <hi>Auguſtus</hi> at <hi>Philippi,</hi> and ſo in deſpair deſired his Friend <hi>Stra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to</hi> to kill him.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="biography">
                  <pb n="123" facs="tcp:99029:73"/>
                  <head>CAIUS CASSIUS LONGINUS.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">U.C. <hi>710.</hi>
                     </note>
                     <hi>Caius Caſſius Longinus</hi> was Quaeſtor in <hi>Syria</hi> under <hi>Craſſus,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Before Ch. <hi>40.</hi>
                     </note> and after he was ſlain, retreated into <hi>Syria</hi> with the Remainder of the Army. He beat <hi>Oſaces,</hi> King <hi>Orodes'</hi>'s General, at the River <hi>Orontes</hi> in <hi>Syria.</hi> He was nick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>named <hi>Caryota,</hi> becauſe he bought up the Dates in <hi>Syria,</hi> and ſold them at an unreaſonable rate. When he was Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bune of the People he oppoſed <hi>Caeſar,</hi> and in the Civil War ſerved under <hi>Pompey,</hi> as his Admiral. However <hi>Caeſar</hi> pardoned him, thô after all, he and <hi>Brutus</hi> were the chief of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpirators that aſſaſſined him, and cried out to one that was afraid to kill him, <hi>I would have you ſtab him even through me.</hi> Then having raiſed a great Army, and joined <hi>Brutus</hi> in <hi>Macedonia,</hi> was overcome by <hi>Antony</hi> at <hi>Philippi,</hi> where, thinking that <hi>Brutus</hi> ſuffered the ſame ill Fortune with himſelf, tho he really had worſted <hi>Caeſar,</hi> he bade his Freed
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:99029:74"/>Man <hi>Pandarus</hi> put an end to his un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy Life. But ſome ſay that <hi>Antony</hi> cryed out, <hi>I have overcome him,</hi> before he had notice of his Death.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="biography">
                  <head>SEXTUS POMPEIUS.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Sextus Pompeius,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">U.C. <hi>714.</hi>
                     </note> after his Overthrow at <hi>Munda</hi> in <hi>Spain,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Before Ch. <hi>36.</hi>
                     </note> and his Brother <hi>Cnaeus</hi>'s Death, got together the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mainder of the Army, and paſſed over into <hi>Sicily,</hi> where he broke open the Work-Houſes, and arming the Slaves, block'd up the Sea, and plagued <hi>Italy,</hi> with want of Proviſion, by taking all the Ships that traffick'd thither. This good Succeſs at Sea ſo puffed him up, that he declared himſelf the Son of <hi>Neptune,</hi> and ſacrific'd to him Bulls, with gilt Horns, and a Horſe. He was facetious in Converſation, for du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the Peace when he treated on Shipboard <hi>Antony</hi> and <hi>Auguſtus Caeſar,</hi> he is reported to have ſaid, not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>properly, <hi>Hae ſunt meae Carinae:</hi> which might be taken in two Senſes, <hi>Theſe are
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:99029:74"/>my Ships;</hi> or, <hi>This is my Houſe:</hi> which <hi>Antony</hi> had taken poſſeſſion of in the Street at <hi>Rome</hi> called <hi>Carinae.</hi> But ſoon after <hi>Antony</hi> broke the League, and <hi>Sextus</hi> being beat at Sea by <hi>Agrippa, Auguſtus</hi>'s Admiral, fled into <hi>Aſia,</hi> and was killed by <hi>Antony</hi>'s Soldiers.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="biography">
                  <head>MARC ANTONY.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">U.C. <hi>721.</hi>
                     </note>
                     <hi>Marc Antony</hi> was <hi>Julius Caeſar</hi>'s Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panion in all his Expeditions,<note place="margin">Before Ch. <hi>29.</hi>
                     </note> at the Feaſts dedicated to <hi>Pan,</hi> kept on the Fifteenth of <hi>February,</hi> he offered to put a Diadem upon his Head; and when he was killed, made an Order that Divine Honors ſhould be paid him: he dealt perfidiouſly with <hi>Auguſtus Caeſar,</hi> but was beaten by him at <hi>Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tina,</hi> ſtarved out of <hi>Peruſium,</hi> and fled into <hi>Gaul,</hi> where he joined himſelf with <hi>Lepidus,</hi> and ſlew <hi>Decimus Brutus,</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving firſt corrupted his Army. Thus having recruited his Forces, he return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed into <hi>Italy,</hi> and was in favour again with <hi>Caeſar.</hi> When he was <hi>Triumvir</hi>
                     <pb n="126" facs="tcp:99029:75"/>his Uncle <hi>Lucius Caeſar</hi> was the firſt Man that he proſcribed. When he was ſent Commander into <hi>Syria,</hi> he made War upon the <hi>Parthians,</hi> and was ſo beaten by them, that he ſcarce brought off with him a third part of 15 Legions into <hi>Aegypt,</hi> where he fell in love with <hi>Cleopatra,</hi> and was routed by <hi>Auguſtus</hi> in a Sea-Fight on the Coaſt of <hi>Actium.</hi> Whence he returned to <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dria,</hi> and ſitting on his Throne in his Royal Robes, killed himſelf.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="biography">
                  <head>CLEOPATRA <hi>Queen of Aegypt.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Cleopatra,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">U.C. <hi>721.</hi>
                     </note> the Daughter of <hi>Ptolemy,</hi> King of <hi>Aegypt,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Before Ch. <hi>29.</hi>
                     </note> being baniſhed by <hi>Ptolemey</hi> who was both her Husband and Brother, for endeavouring to deprive him of his Kingdom; in the Civil Was preſented her ſelf to <hi>Caeſar</hi> at <hi>Alexandria,</hi> and by her Beauty and Careſſes prevailed upon him to kill <hi>Ptolemey,</hi> and ſettle the Kingdom upon her. She was ſo lewd, that ſhe
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:99029:75"/>would often proſtitute her ſelf; and ſo beautiful, that many loſt their Lives to poſſeſs her Love. After this ſhe joyned her Intereſt with <hi>Antony,</hi> and was beaten with him at <hi>Actium,</hi> and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der pretenee of ſacrificing to his Ghoſt at his Tomb, ſhe put Serpents to her Breaſts, and died.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:99029:76" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:99029:76" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:99029:77"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:99029:77"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:99029:78"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:99029:78"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:99029:79"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:99029:79"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:99029:80"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:99029:80"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:99029:81"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:99029:82"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:99029:83"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:99029:83"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:99029:84"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:99029:84"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:99029:85"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:99029:85"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:99029:86"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:99029:86"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:99029:87"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:99029:87" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:99029:88"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:99029:88"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:99029:89"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:99029:89"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:99029:90"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:99029:90"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:99029:91"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:99029:91"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:99029:92"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:99029:92"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:99029:93"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:99029:93"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:99029:94"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:99029:94"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:99029:95"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:99029:95"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:99029:96"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:99029:96"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:99029:97"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:99029:97"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:99029:98"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:99029:98"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:99029:99"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:99029:99"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:99029:100"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:99029:100"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:99029:101"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:99029:101"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:99029:102"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:99029:102"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="32" facs="tcp:99029:103"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:99029:103"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:99029:104"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="35" facs="tcp:99029:104"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="36" facs="tcp:99029:105"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="37" facs="tcp:99029:105"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="38" facs="tcp:99029:106"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="39" facs="tcp:99029:106"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="40" facs="tcp:99029:107"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="41" facs="tcp:99029:107"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="42" facs="tcp:99029:108"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="43" facs="tcp:99029:108"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="44" facs="tcp:99029:109"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="45" facs="tcp:99029:109"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="46" facs="tcp:99029:110"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="47" facs="tcp:99029:110"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="48" facs="tcp:99029:111"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="49" facs="tcp:99029:111"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="50" facs="tcp:99029:112"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="51" facs="tcp:99029:112"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="52" facs="tcp:99029:113"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="53" facs="tcp:99029:113"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="54" facs="tcp:99029:114"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="55" facs="tcp:99029:114"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="56" facs="tcp:99029:115"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="57" facs="tcp:99029:115"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
